<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Great Britain's just complaint for her late measures, present sufferings, and the future miseries she is exposed to with the best, safest, and most effectual way of securing and establishing her religion, government, liberty, and property upon good and lasting foundations : fully and clearly discovered in answer to two late pamphlets concerning the pretended French invasion.</title>
            <author>Montgomery, James, Sir, d. 1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2504</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30525</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11348640</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11348640</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47544</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51196)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1466:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Great Britain's just complaint for her late measures, present sufferings, and the future miseries she is exposed to with the best, safest, and most effectual way of securing and establishing her religion, government, liberty, and property upon good and lasting foundations : fully and clearly discovered in answer to two late pamphlets concerning the pretended French invasion.</title>
                  <author>Montgomery, James, Sir, d. 1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 61 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCII [1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Montgomery by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Errata p. 61.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47544:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47544:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>GREAT BRITAIN</hi>'s JUST COMPLAINT FOR HER Late <hi>Meaſures,</hi> Preſent <hi>Sufferings,</hi> And the Future <hi>Miſeries</hi> She is expoſed to.</p>
            <p>With the Beſt, Safeſt, and moſt Effectual WAY of Securing and Eſtabliſhing Her Religion, Government, <hi>Liberty &amp; Property,</hi> Upon Good and Laſting Foundations.</p>
            <p>Fully and Clearly Diſcovered, In ANSWER To Two Late Pamphlets, concerning the <hi>Pretended French Invaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year MDCXCII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47544:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47544:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Great Britain</hi>'s Juſt Complaint FOR Her Late <hi>Meaſures,</hi> Preſent <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and the Future <hi>Miſeries</hi> She is Expoſed to.</head>
            <p>THE laſt great Revolution in <hi>Britain</hi> (which doth ſo much exerciſe the Heads, Hands, Purſes and Pens, of the Inhabitants of this Iſland) is not to be paralel'd by any Inſtance from ancient or modern Hiſtory. When we have ranſackt the Annals of all the Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> and travell'd as far as the <hi>Indies</hi> to find an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, we ſhall at laſt be forced to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, after all Circumſtances are exactly weighed, That we have been blindly following the Dictates of our own perſonal Prejudices and intoxicated Judgments, rather than tracing the Footſteps of our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, or of the moſt zealous Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of publick Liberties in other Nations. I do not deny, that in every Province and Kingdom of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe we may find Inſtances where Subjects have been at laſt neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by force of Arms to ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their Religion and Liberties, againſt ſuch violent and repeated Acts of Tyranny in their Princes, as did viſibly endanger the Frame of the Government it ſelf, as well as the Safety of every Individual: And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Princes have loſt their Crowns by a tract of Cruelties and Exorbitances in Government, and an incorrigible Obſtinacy and Deafneſs to all the humble Petitions and repeated Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of their Subjects.</p>
            <p>But we ſcorned to be confined within ſuch ancient Rules, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated by the Practices of our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, or to be taught at the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence or by the Experience of others. We have walked without Guides, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt dark and dangerous Precipices: Our Fears have overrun our Reaſon; we have taken things upon Truſt, without ſearching them to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47544:3"/>
and we have been impoſed upon, by the cunning and artificial Diſguiſes of ſelf-deſigning and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Men, to overlook a moſt infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible way of ſecuring Liberty and Property to all future Ages; which the Ambition of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the hard Circumſtances of our own King, had put into our hands. We have vacated a Throne, for the pretended Diſertion of a Prince, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently forced away by a ſurprizing Defection of his Children, Servants, Subjects and Soldiers; and under the terror of dangers threatning his Life and Liberty. We have juſtified this Severity, by enumerating Miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in Government; which, though Errors and Miſtakes, were very far from overturning Foundations; and which the King was put upon by the artifice and cunning of his Son in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law, who was graſping at his Crown: And we have obſtinately refuſed all Treaties, when offered; whereby Grievances might have been redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and provided againſt for the future; and we have ventured upon ſuch Steps as have no Precedent, and furniſhed an Example for Hiſtory, which will be found too deſperate and expenſive for imitation.</p>
            <p>Yet ſo far hath this Poyſon ſpread and diffuſed it ſelf, that though the pretended Reaſons of our Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings appear at laſt to be empty, falſe and forged; though the principal Actors are aſhamed of their former grounds, and love the ſound of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> better than that of a <hi>Deliverance,</hi> and are countenanced in it by the Practiſes as well as Inclination and Maxims of our preſent Monarch; there are ſome People who would gladly continue the Cheat, and amuſe us ſtill with a Hodge-podge of <hi>Right of Succeſſion, Election,</hi> and <hi>Conquest,</hi> and the lofty and agreeable ſound of <hi>Religion, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Property;</hi> which appears to be as little the care as it was the deſign of our principal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, That we have of late been entertained with two famous Pamphlets, the one entituled <hi>The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of the French Invaſion exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;</hi> Licenſed, or rather written, by the E. of <hi>Nottingham:</hi> The other is <hi>A Letter to a Friend, concerning the French Invaſion;</hi> which muſt be the Offspring of a Perſon of equal Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with the former, ſince his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter ſtamps it legitimate, without a Licenſe. Theſe two Pieces do not in the leaſt anſwer the Figure which the Authors, who are aſſign'd them, make in the World: For all along, they falſifie, diſguiſe, or abſolutely conceal Matter of fact; they labour to impoſe Falſhoods for Truths, and their baſe Alloy as good Coin upon us: They advance Poſitions for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Maxims, which have been controverted all the World over, and upon this Sandy Foundation they raiſe their Building; and their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings are either falſe, ſophiſticated, or moſt concluſive on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>To make good this Charge, and acquit my ſelf of the Duty I owe my Country and fellow Subjects, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing my Mite towards the recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying their Judgments in ſuch a nice and important Affair, wherein our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47544:3"/>
own Peace and Happineſs, as well as that of our Poſterity, is ſo much wrapt up. I ſhall endeavour to make a full and diſtinct Anſwer to theſe Two Pamphlets, by a true un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſſed and impartial Deduction of Matter of fact, by ſeting out the publick Councils, Deſigns, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of particular Perſons, in their true Light, without thoſe Diſguiſes which were Art-fully thrown over them; and by their own Reaſons and Maxims, concluding a great deal more forcibly againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And to deal fairly by them, I ſhall confine my ſelf to thoſe very Arguments, which are aſſigned by the Author of <hi>The French Invaſion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined,</hi> as the Motives upon which the Reſtauration of King <hi>James</hi> is deſired and endeavoured; <hi>viz. The repairing the Injury done to the King, the ſetling the Government upon its old Baſis, the delivering us from the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions we ſuffer under the preſent King, and the ſecuring the Proteſtant Religion for the future.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no Engliſh-man but muſt allow theſe Conſiderations to be Grave, Weighty and Important; and if as True as Conſiderable, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently concluſive and perſuaſive for a ſpeedy Reſtauration. I will then enter upon a particular Enquiry; and I do not diſpair, before I have done, to eſtabliſh the Truth, as well as the Importance of thoſe Reaſons, againſt the Cavils of thoſe Authors: I joyn them together, becauſe their Reaſonings are much the ſame, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually levelled againſt the aforeſaid Motives, and muſt ſtand or fall to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt Motive <hi>Of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing the Injury done to King</hi> James. If it can be made appear, That he was unjuſtly upon falſe Pretences deprived of his Birth-right by his Subjects, who by Nature and Oaths were bound to defend him in it; then muſt it be acknowleged a Duty by all, as well as thoſe Authors, to repair that Injury done him, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring his Right again. I ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my ſelf particularly to the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Injuſtice done him, ſince upon that a great part of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie depends, and moſt of the Reaſons aſſigned by theſe Authors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Reſtauration will fall to the ground: In doing of which, I muſt look higher than the begining of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign; the early and unnatural Ambition of the Pr: of <hi>Orange,</hi> as well as the neceſſary connection and ſeries of Affairs, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige me unto it.</p>
            <p>It was not the danger which our Religion and Liberties were threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with, from the Deſigns and bad Adminiſtration of King <hi>James,</hi> and a tender regard to the Britiſh Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, for their Love and Reſpect to his deareſt Conſort, and Himſelf, with the Intereſt which his Birth and Marriage gave him in us, firſt indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to look to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards theſe Kingdoms and our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. The late King <hi>Charles</hi> (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of all the tenderneſs he had diſcovered for that Prince's Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and care for his Intereſts, in eſpouſing them ſo vigourſly upon all occaſions againſt the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who would gladly have ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47544:4"/>
themſelves, by depreſſing him and his Family, againſt thoſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Fears they lay under, for their beloved Rights and Liberties) was the firſt that felt the Effects of his Nephew's towring and boundleſs Ambition. No ſooner did the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> find himſelf reinſtated, by the Authority and Intereſt of his Uncle, in the Poſts of Grandure poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by his Father and Predeceſſors, and ſo put into a Condition to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear upon the Stage, and mingle in the greateſt Affairs of <hi>Europe,</hi> but he gave looſe Ranes to his Ambition, to range where-ever it could perch and fix; without being reſtrained or frightned by thoſe common Rules or Barriers, which Morality and Religion had placed as Spoaks too mean in his Opinion to ſtop the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reere of a bold and daring Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Britain</hi> was the Place he fixed his Eye upon; neither could Relation, or Gratitude, place any rubs in his way. The lazy Temper of that Monarch, addicted to his Pleaſures, and his being without Children, the Religion of his Brother, and want of Male Iſſue, together with his own Allyance with the Royal Blood, and ſome Diſcontents of the People, which were begotten and heightned by the Addreſſes and Malice of a few Grandees, promiſed him a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Harveſt in return to his Cabals, and Cajoling Inſinuations; upon which thoſe Grandees were applied unto; and as quick and hearty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns made by them, with aſſurance of Zeal, Dependance and Fidelity, being glad of ſo conſiderable a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. Hence ſprang all thoſe fatal Diviſions which ſo long time exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed that Prince, his Councils, and Parliaments.</p>
            <p>To ſpirit this Party in <hi>England,</hi> and to fix himſelf one Degree nearer the Crown, which he ſo much long'd for, the Prince made his Addreſſes, and was Married to the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> much againſt the inclination both of the King and Duke, who did very well foreſee the Conſequence, and were afraid of ſo near a Conjunction with ſo reſtleſs a Spirit. But it is well known who diſpoſed the King to agree to the Match; for which, and other good Services then in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying his Maſter, he is well rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded now, rather than for any Merits he had to plead upon this Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>After this Match, our Diviſions and Diſcontents paſt all Bounds; nothing leſs than the interruption of the Royal Line, by a Bill of Excluſion, would ſatisfie. I know the danger of our Religion, from a Popiſh Succeſſor, was pretended; but the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s immediate Succeſſion to the Crown, in the Right of his Princeſs, was the thing truly intended by the Prince's Agents, and Privadoes: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but ſuch a hidden ſecret Deſign, could have inclined ſo many Men of Senſe and Reaſon, to refuſe the great Conceſſions was offered 'em; which without Danger, or the bad Conſequences of neglecting a juſt Title, did equally ſecure Religion and Liberty. To this Project were Sacrificed all thoſe great and mighty Securities, which K. <hi>Charles</hi> would
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47544:4"/>
willingly have Granted in favour of our Religion and Liberties, to be rid of that troubleſome Bill of Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and thus we loſt the greateſt, and beſt Eſtabliſhment we ever had in our view; and which would le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally, peaceably and willingly, have been ſetled upon us, without any farther trouble, danger or expence: So early did this Prince's Ambition become fatal to our Liberties and Properties.</p>
            <p>Hence ſprang all thoſe Councils and Meaſures, which did ſo much Diſcontent the People; and put that King upon the <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> Project, thereby to temper and qualifie Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, which the Cabals and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations of the Prince had render'd ſo warm and uneaſie to him. Hence ſprang that Ferment, and thoſe bad Humors, which gave Life and Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Pretences, who all a long had been made a Stale by ſome; though the Prince lay cloſe at the bottom, and ſeemed to favour the Man; until at laſt he perceived that the Duke did in earneſt catch at that he ſo much longed for himſelf. With what regret, yea indignation, muſt every Engliſh Breaſt be filled upon that bleſſed occaſion we loſt, which might have prevented our preſent Expence of Blood and Treaſure, and all thoſe Fears and Miſeries we are now groaning under, and know not when we ſhall be at an end of? It is with unſpeakable Grief I am obliged to remember ſo great a Loſs; nor do I mention any thing, but what is very well known for a Truth to ſome Perſons yet alive, and which I have ſeen clearly verified by ſome convincing Diſpatches which are yet extant, and which ſhall be carefully preſerved until they may be with ſafety produced. Doth not Sir <hi>W. Temple,</hi> in his <hi>Memoirs,</hi> licenced and publiſhed of late, acknowledge the greateſt part of what is here aſſerted? as if, in this reforming Age, People were to make their Court by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of Services, for which their Poſterity may have reaſon to curſe their Aſhes. Thus we ſee what fatal Influences the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Ambition had ſcattered upon our Councils and Meaſures, during the later end of K. <hi>Charles</hi> his Reign: Neither will he be found leſs active and ſucceſsful, by himſelf and Agents, during K. <hi>James</hi>'s Adminiſtration, as will appear from a particular En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the pretended <hi>Abdication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſtrange and myſterious word, which to this day is not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, neither can be explained, nor rightly fitted to what was intended by it, either by the Authors of it, or by any body elſe, was firſt made uſe of in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> ſome Ages ago; and begot that fatal Srug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle between the <hi>Anjouin</hi> and <hi>Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganian</hi> Factions, which at laſt quite ruined that flouriſhing Kingdom, and brought it under a foreign Yoke, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which it continues to this day. I ſhall not criticize upon it, nor examin how improperly it is applied in the Caſe of King <hi>James,</hi> (though that be obvious enough to any Man who underſtands the Civil Law, or the proper and genuine ſignification of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47544:5"/>
the Word) but ſhall only enquire into the ſubject matter, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Senſe of our Reformers, amounted to <hi>Abdication</hi> &amp; a <hi>Vacancy;</hi> and that is King <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Diſertion</hi> and <hi>Invaſion</hi> of the fundamental Laws and Liberties of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt, how properly his being forced away may be called a <hi>Diſertion,</hi> will beſt appear from a true Narrative of Matter of fact; which I ſhall give the Reader: And though it may contain ſeveral things which are not generally known, and yet contribute exceedingly to the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this point, I ſhall deliver no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Truths, which can be made evident, either by Letters, or Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence above all exception. No ſooner was the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> landed, but it quickly appeared to the World how ſtrangely ſucceſsful his Agents had been in their Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations. The Poyſon was univerſally ſpread, and the Pretences of his <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> greedily ſwallowed down without Examination; though I ſhall make it appear, before I have done, That it was partly forged, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it ever intended to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. There was nothing ſound or untainted in the whole Kingdom: His Children run away from him; the Clergy juggle with him; his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick and menial Servants betray him; his Subjects flock in to the P. of <hi>Orange;</hi> his Army diſert; and the very Creatures which he had raiſed from the Duſt form Deſigns to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver up his Perſon.</p>
            <p>Was not this a Scene, the moſt wonderful and aſtoniſhing that was ever preſented upon the Stage of human Affairs? What ground had the King to think that his Perſon could be with any manner of Safety, amongſt a People who had thrown off all Tyes and Duties which could ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally be depended upon in the like caſe? When that natural Affection which was due from Children to their Parents was quite forgotten; when the Love, Reſpect, Service, and Gratitude, which is due from Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to their Maſter and Benefactor, was entirely thrown off, and unheard of Treachery cheriſhed in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? When that Allegiance which is due from Subjects to their Prince was debauched, and running into another Channel? When that Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which was due from Soldiers, (both as Subjects, and Men who make a particular Profeſſion of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) to their Prince, General and Nurſing Father, was ſo generally corrupted, that he was advertiſed by his General Officers, <hi>That the Army was quite poiſoned, and would not fight?</hi> When his own Miniſters and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors were in Pay and Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the Invader, and puſhing him into Councils and Meaſures, which might encreaſe the preſent Ferment, and facilitate the Prince's Deſigns? What hopes of Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, or Aſſurance of Safety, could remain, without renouncing all Reaſon, Senſe, and Diſcretion? eſpecially if we conſider that as ſoon as the account came that <hi>Oxford</hi>'s, and <hi>St. Alban</hi>'s Regiment of Horſe commanded by <hi>Langſton,</hi> and <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> and <hi>Heyfort</hi> with their Dragoons,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47544:5"/>
were deſerted and gone into the Prince, he called his General Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Colonels together at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> amongſt which were <hi>Churchil, Kirk, Trelauny, Grafton</hi> and others; and acquainted them, he had called a free Parliament, that he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſecure Religion, Liberty and Property, at their Sitting. He obteſted theſe Officers to let him know if there was any thing farther which they deſired for the Security of their Religion and Liberties, and he would moſt willingly grant it; and withal deſired, That if there was any amongſt them who could not be ſatiſfied, to let him know it, and he would frankly grant them Paſſes for themſelves and Equipage, to go in to the Prince. Upon which, they all anſwer'd chearfully and unanimouſly <hi>That they were fully ſatisfied, and would hazard their Blood, to the laſt drop, in his Service:</hi> And yet how baſely and ungratefully ſome of them afterwards dealt by him, is too well known, and was enough to give that Prince juſt Jealouſies of his own Safety amongſt Men ſo loſt as to all ſenſe of Honour and Integrity.</p>
            <p>And yet ſo loth was this Monarch to part from a People who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken him firſt, though ſurrounded with Fears and Diſtractions, under which any other Perſon would have ſunck, that he made offers of a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; which the Prince accepted, not that he deſigned to come to any Settlement upon it, but becauſe he durſt not unmask himſelf ſo far as to refuſe it; and was in hopes to find ſome Pretext or other to break it off. Upon this, the Commiſſioners met on both ſides, but with ſo little Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, on the Prince's ſide, to come to an Accommodation, which would have bereaved him of that ſweet Morſel he had been ſo long labouring for; nay, he diſcovered ſo firm a Reſolution to attain his ends, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſcrupling any thing, how ſevere ſoever, which could compaſs them; that thoſe noble Lords, who were empower'd by the King to treat for him, did acquaint his Majeſty with the inſuperable Difficulties they met with in their Negotiation; and that they thought themſelves bound in Duty to let him know that his Perſon was not in Safety under the <hi>Power</hi> of a Prince, who by the haughty and rigid Conditions he propoſed, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſed, and his ſtill marching on, notwithſtanding the Treaty, did viſibly enough diſcover ſome farther hidden Deſign. This muſt certainly be thought Warning enough from Perſons who were even then leaning to the ſtrongeſt ſide, and ſo would not have hazarded ſuch advice, unleſs forced to it by Truth and Horror of the Deſign; or put upon it by the Prince himſelf, to frighten the King away, who was ſenſible his Stay did check his Deſigns, and ſo was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be rid of his Perſon ſome way or other.</p>
            <p>Upon this the King thought fit to withdraw; and afterwards ſent the E. of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> from that place, with ſuch ample Conceſſions, and ſuch real diſcoveries of a ſincere In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, to ſatisfie his People to the full, that the Prince was extreamly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47544:6"/>
alarmed upon it, and did plainly ſee the miſcarriage and ruin of all his Deſigns, if <hi>Feverſham</hi>'s Meſſage ſhould be imparted to the Engliſh that were about him; for though there were ſome, who upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions were forward enough to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe the utmoſt Severities againſt the King's Perſon, yet by far the greateſt part for Number, Intereſt and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, were at the bottom for an Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation with the K. which would have ſetled and bettered the Nation; but at the ſame time would have quite daſhed the Prince's Hopes and Expectations; and therefore ſome bold Stroke muſt be given, that ſo much Patience, ſo great Labour, and ſo many Crimes might not be loſt; the Publick Faith muſt be broken, and <hi>Feverſham</hi> muſt be ſecured, without ſo much as acquainting the Perſons of Quality of the Engliſh Nation who were about him with it, though all a long he had preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to act by their Advice. But in ſo nice a Conjunction he was afraid to truſt to their Affection, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well they would have p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y'd more than was fitting, for his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, into the pretended Cauſe of the Earl's Confinement, and his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: the Goodneſs of which would certainly have preſerved the Publick Faith inviolable in the Earl's Perſon, notwithſtanding of the Crime alleg'd againſt him, and continued in the Treaty; whereas by this Method the Meſſage was concealed, the Treaty was quite broken off, and the King would moſt certainly be frightned to ſteal away. After ſuch a ſeries of Defection amongſt all ſorts of People, after ſuch an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſent by Perſons whom he had truſted with the moſt important Concerns of his Crown and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, after ſuch an open Breach of the publick Faith, and after ſuch viſible and open diſcoveries of the Prince's ſecret Deſigns and unlimited Ambition, a Paſſion which never ſcruples to ſacrafice every <hi>Remora</hi> to its Eſtabliſhment where it Predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates; Is there any cool and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Man will cenſure the King's Conduct in disbanding that Army, which had for the moſt part made a Defection from him; and in taking care of his Perſon by a ſpeedy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat from amongſt ſuch wavering Subjects, dangerous and diſingenuous Enemies. But in farther Evidence of the King's unwillingneſs to part from his People, and of the Prince's fix d and determinate Reſolutions to force him to as great a diſtance as he could, being always jealous of a Reconcilement, which would have quite buried his ambitious Thoughts and Deſigns; I ſhall give the World a particular account of the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Steps taken by either Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to their ſeveral Deſigns.</p>
            <p>The King, when he came to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> ſent a Meſſage to Sir <hi>Thomas Stamp,</hi> now Mayor, and to Sir <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lewis,</hi> two eminent Aldermen of that City; deſiring them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint their Brethren, and others of the Common Council, That he was reſolved to put himſelf into the hands of the City, there to remain until by a free Parliament he had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47544:6"/>
given all Satisfaction to his People, by ſecuring their Religion, Liberties and Properties, to the full; hoping, that in the mean time, they would take care to guard and ſecure his Perſon. The foreſaid Perſons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated this Meſſage, as they were deſired; but by the influence and intereſt of Sir <hi>Robert Clayton</hi> the offer was refuſed, and the ſecurity of his Perſon would not be aſſured to him. Here is plain demonſtration, both of the King's Willingneſs to piece up with his People, and of the Danger which threatned his Perſon. When the King came from <hi>Feverſham</hi> to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Zuyleſtein</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him, at <hi>Somerſet houſe,</hi> a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Prince, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to have reached him before he came from <hi>Feverſham;</hi> wherein he was deſired, but in the Style of a Command, not to come any nearer <hi>London</hi> than <hi>Rocheſter:</hi> To which the King very meekly returned an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>That he would have complied with the Letter, had it come ſooner to his hands.</hi> Can there be any more doubt, after this, of the Prince's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and ambitious Deſigns, to put ſuch a Reſtraint upon a Monarch in his own Dominions, whoſe undoubted Title he had acknowleged, both by his Declaration and a Treaty: This was a piece of Haughtineſs and Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence above all Example, except what his own future Practices hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed us with.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the King came to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> he wrote to the Prince, inviting him to St. <hi>James</hi>'s, allowing him his own Dutch Guards to ſecure his Perſon, and aſſuring him, That upon their Interview he would fully ſatisfie the intent of his Declaration. But this was no ſatisfaction to the Prince: He had a ſecret and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed aim at the Crown; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he could gain that point, he liked it the better that it were Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with all the Power he ſo much complained of in his Declaration: His Conduct ſince hath ſufficiently cleared this to theſe Nations: An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview, which was ſo much deſired by the King, did not ſuit with this darling Project; he could neither well ask it, nor expect to have it granted. Beſides, he found the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the Peoples Affections, which had run ſo ſwiftly towards himſelf, was then at a Stand, and in danger to be turned into another Channel, if the King remained at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and at liberty to apply himſelf to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining of his Subjects Hearts; which he was ſincerely reſolved to court and acquire at any rate, being free from the bad Influences and Advices of thoſe Miniſters which were in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy with the Prince. Upon all which, it was reſolved that Count <hi>Solmes</hi> ſhould poſſeſs the ſeveral Poſts at <hi>Whitehall</hi> with Dutch Guards, and make the King a Priſoner: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two a Clock in the Morning he received Orders from the Prince, by the Mouths of three noble Lords, to be gone immediately from his own Palace; and accordingly he was ſent Priſoner to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> attended by Dutch Guards, and all this perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with unſpeakable Rudeneſs and Indignities done to his Perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:47544:7"/>He was diſturbed at an unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hour, with a Sentence of Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from his own Palace, paſſed upon him by his Son-in-law, who pretended only to ſettle and fix his Crown by redreſſing of Grievances, and that Sentence pronounced unto him by three of his own Subjects, who accompanied it with ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly Severities, which their fears of a courſer Treatment, if he ſtaid, put them upon. He was refuſed his own Guards to attend him, and his own Coach to carry him to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> though he declared, That he could not travel by Water in ſo cold a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, againſt Wind and Tide, without greatly endangering his Health. Good God! that ſuch Barbarities ſhould be practiſed, and afterwards juſtified, by Chriſtians, which Pagans and Infidels would be aſhamed of.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the King ſtaid at <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and during the Seſſions of thoſe Lords and Commons, who firſt put the Adminiſtration of Affairs into the Prince's Hand, and moved for cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Convention, he ſent a Meſſage to the preſent B of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> which he deſired might be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to the reſt of the Biſhops; acquainting him with his Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to come either publickly or privately, and put himſelf into the Hands of my Lords the Biſhops to be under their Protection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, until at their Sight, and by their Advice, he had fully ſettled and ſecured every thing in a free Parliament. This Meſſage the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> did impart to the reſt; and their return to it was, That they could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, either publickly or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, under their Protection; for in that caſe they would be reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for his Safety, and they were not in a Condition to ſecure him againſt the Ambition of the Prince, who was reſolved to accompliſh his Deſigns; and ſurrounded with ſo many Troops, after ſo many Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements given him of the danger his Perſon was in, by People who might know it, and whoſe Teſtimony was not to be ſuſpected; and thoſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements fortified and confirmed, by the Prince's ſtrange and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Carriage, in breaking the publick Treaty, in impriſoning my Lord <hi>Feverſham</hi> contrary to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, thereby to elude the Effects of his Meſſage, in refuſing a perſonal Treaty, depriving him of his Liberty, putting him under Guards, and in baniſhing him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periouſly and unmannerly from his own Houſes. After ſo many fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Applications to the Prince, to the City, and to the Biſhops, only to be ſecured as to his Perſon, until by a free Parliament he had given full Satisfaction to his People. Can there be any Perſon who is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Bankrupt, as to common Senſe and Reaſon, who will blame the King for withdrawing, and thereby endeavouring to put himſelf in Safety? And it is evident, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all thoſe ineffectual Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, he was reſolved upon every occaſion to court his Subjects to return to their Duty: Witneſs his Letters addreſſed to ſeveral Members of his Privy Council; and alſo that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47544:7"/>
Letter written from St. <hi>Germains,</hi> and deſigned for the Convention of Eſtates, which they would not ſo much as receive or read.</p>
            <p>I would now gladly know after what manner, and upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, in what ſenſe, and for what reaſon the King can be ſaid to have deſerted. <hi>Deſertion,</hi> according to common ſenſe and acceptation, is a voluntary Neglect and Withdrawing his Perſon, Care and Influences, from attending that Adminiſtration, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and Exerciſe of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is due from him to the People committed to his Charge; when no Force compell'd him, no Danger threatned him, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were willing to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tain him. Is this applicable to the King's Caſe? May not the Invading his Dominions with foreign Troops and an armed Power, the Impriſonment of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, putting him under Guards of Foreigners, and baniſhing him from his own Houſes, be properly enough called a Force? May not thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Indignities done him by the Prince, and thoſe Advertiſements given him by ſeveral Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Knowl dge, and Intereſt, of his hard and difficult Circumſtances, be very well called Dangers, according to the common Rules of Prudence and Diſcretion? With what Senſe can the univerſal Defection of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Servants, Soldiers and Subjects, the rejecting all Treaties, whether perſonal or by Proxie, the Refuſal of all Applications made by him to the City, Biſhops, and Convention of Eſtates, be underſtood an unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his Subjects to part with him, or a voluntary Withdrawing or Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect on his ſide? We muſt renounce common Senſe, and quite invert the Nature of things, before a With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing ſo circumſtantiated will paſs upon the ſober part of Mankind for a Deſertion.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it is a Maxim laid down by the Author of the <hi>Pretences of the French Invaſion examined,</hi> p 4 l. 3. and downwards, <hi>That where a King or Queen is ſubmitted to, and owned by Oaths, and other Methods required in ſuch Caſes, the King himſelf is not at Liberty to give up his own Power, and conſequently cannot Deſert; much leſs can the People wreſt it from him A Man hath himſelf much more Right to lay down that Power which is legally veſted in him, than any other Perſon or Perſons can have to take it from him</hi> I hope this learned Gentleman will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us the Benefit of his own Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims, which we are willing to admit of. It cannot be denied King <hi>James</hi> was ſubmitted unto, and owned by Oaths and all other Methods requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in ſuch Caſes; and ſo not at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to give up his own Power, thô never ſo willing: And conſequently this pretended Deſertion muſt march off the Stage, according to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's own Rules.</p>
            <p>But the Disbanding of the Army, in the Senſe of this Author and others, was ſo illegal a Step, that it muſt paſs for his diſſolving of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Why truly, common Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence adviſed the Diſcarding of an Army, which had dealt ſo treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly with their Prince and Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47544:8"/>
And I would gladly know, what Statute this Meaſure of the King's treſpaſſed upon. I challenge the Author to point it out to us. I have heard it alleged, That the King could not raiſe and maintain an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my without the Conſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But his power of Disbanding was never yet queſtioned, much leſs made a Crime: If the firſt be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable, the laſt muſt be much more ſo. From what has been ſaid, I hope the <hi>Deſertion</hi> is quite ſhut out of doors: The Reaſons adduced make unanſwerably againſt it; and the Pamphleteer's own Maxims knock it dead without Mercy; by which the greateſt part of the Author's Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet and Reaſonings falls to the ground, ſince he goeth all along up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Suppoſition that the People were ſtill willing to have acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged his Rights and ſecured their own, to have treated and come to an Accommodation with him: as alſo that the Prince never propoſed any thing, but to have Grievances fairly redreſſed, which was ſtill inſiſted on by the Prince and People in the moſt humble and uſual Methods: But that the King wilfully deſerted, threw up the Government, refuſed all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and left them in a perfect Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, to ſhift for themſelves. The Falſity of all which is already plainly enough demonſtrated, and the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ication</hi> muſt halt, having loſt the better half of its Foundation.</p>
            <p>I come next to examine the Male-Adminiſtration, which makes up the other part of this Structure; in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of which, I do not intend to play the Advocate, to defend and juſtifie any Breaches made upon the Laws and Liberties of my Country: I am as tender of thoſe great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns as any Man can be; I love them as well; I value them as high, and ſhall be always ready to hazard as far for their Eſtabliſhment, as a good <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> who knows their Worth, ought to do. And perhaps I have given better Evidences of this, than the Authors of theſe Pamphlets can bring for themſelves, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their Fuſtian Words and high Pretences.</p>
            <p>But Miſtakes in Government will be ſlipping in under the beſt Reigns; and it is not every Error can furniſh a good Reaſon for ſuch important Revolutions, ſuch general Defections, ſuch deviations from that Duty which is due to Princes from the Obligation of Oaths, the Tyes of Nature, and the Laws of the Land; and for dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Kings, inverting the nature of the Monarchy, and the interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Royal Line and Succeſſion. Such Alterations have been accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied in all Ages with ſuch Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Convulſions, Blood, Ruine and Deſolation, that nothing but the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Reſcue of the Government it ſelf, and of all the publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Rights which are wrapt up in it, from a clear, plain, viſible, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable, and otherwiſe unavoidable Ruine and Deſtruction, with a Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and Conviction that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy propoſed will prove feaſible and ſucceſsful, without running us into the ſame dangers and difficulties; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n furniſh the leaſt ſhadow or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47544:8"/>
for Experiments which are to be attended with ſuch Dangers, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the Breach of ſo many ſacred Tyes and Obligations, and Supported with ſuch Expence of Blood and Treaſure.</p>
            <p>We ought to be very ſure, That the Errors complained of would certainly have overturned all Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and entirely robbed us of our Rights; That thoſe Errors did certainly ariſe from the natural Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Prince himſelf, obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately and incorrigibly bent to purſue them to the utmoſt, whatever the Conſequence might be, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Impulſe of corrupted Miniſters, from a Deſign to ruine him and make a Property of us, in ſerving the ambitious but guilded Pretences of ſome other Perſon; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we run headlong into ſuch Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. But alas! I am afraid we are not able to ſtand this Tryal, which every cool and thinking Man muſt allow to be very reaſonable; and upon an exact and impartial Enquiry it will be found, That with all this Buſtle, Noiſe, Blood, Treaſure, and Pretence for publick Good and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; we have been deſtroying what we have built up; graſping unſucceſsfully at that amidſt the dangers, Cruelties, and Expences of a War, and with the Breach of ſo many ſacred Tyes and Engagements, which we might have Inſured to our ſelves and Poſterity with much eaſe and innocence; and wreathing a Yoke about our N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cks, which will gaul and pinch us more ſeverely than what we endeavoured to throw off.</p>
            <p>The Male-Adminiſtrations charged upon King <hi>James</hi> by thoſe Pamphlet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers, are ſhortly ſumm'd up by them in the <hi>Weſtern Severities, the High Commiſſion, the turning out of Office all good Proteſtants, the attempting to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe all the Penal Laws, the putting unqualified Men into Places of Truſt, Profit and Power; the exerciſe of the Diſpenſing Power, the excluding the Fellows of</hi> Magdalen Colledge, <hi>and putting in Papiſts; with the Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Tryal of the Biſhops.</hi> It ſeems theſe Authors are of opinion that any Reaſon, how weak and unconcluſive ſoever it be, ſhould paſs as good Coin upon us, ſince they come from ſuch Magiſterial and Florid Pens. But if they deſigned that their Authority alone ſhould paſs for Reaſon amongſt us, they ought to have ſubjoyned their Names, to add thereby ſome Value and Weight to Arguments and Grounds, by far too weak in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſupport ſo lofty a Building as is founded upon them. Some of the Miſgovernments here enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which I have exactly Copied from p. 6. l. 8. and downwards, of <hi>The Pretences of the French Invaſion examined,</hi> are falſe, others maliciouſly aggravated, and the reſt the King was forced upon by the Importunity of Miniſters who were gained by the Prince, and offered ſuch Advices only with a deſign to render him odious to the People, and thereby to diſpoſe them for this happy Revolution, which hath ſince fallen out. But to examine them ſeverally;</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Severities, I believe it will not be deny'd, even
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47544:9"/>
by this Government, that the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> his Invaſion was a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; and that the Lives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of all ingaged in it, were by the Laws of the Land forfeited to Juſtice. I am heartily ſorry that ſo much Blood was ſhed by the Hands of the common Executioner; but it is very well known to many Perſons of Honour and Quality, that thoſe great Severities were only to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to the inſolent and cruel Temper of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ries, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llexſen</hi> and <hi>Kirk;</hi> that the King himſelf was extreamly offended at it, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately put a ſtop to their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſo ſoon as he was acquainted with them: And it is ſtrange enough how this comes to be charged ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome upon King <hi>James,</hi> by the Champions of th s Government, ſince King <hi>William</hi> by his a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>arcing and employing of <hi>Kirk</hi> and <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xſen,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> plainly diſcovered to the World, That either he did not look upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>verities to be unſeaſonable or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or alſo that he loved them the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for th ir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and bloody Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for his Service and Deſigns; otherwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſuch Butchers would not have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced by a Reforming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The High Commiſſion Court I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>: But we know very well <hi>Who</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dviſed it; and we ſee one of the moſt active Members of it in a fair Way of Preferment <hi>now;</hi> and certainly our preſent King would not honour ſuch a Man, or truſt his Affairs into his hands, if he lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Commiſſion to have been a good ground for <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The turning out of Office all good Proteſtants, and the putting of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualified Men into all Places of Truſt, Profit and Povver, is a large Strain of Eloquence, which though like the uſual Flights of the ſuppoſed Author, is too light and falſe for ſo grave and weighty a Subject: For many Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Profit, Truſt, and Povver, were kept filled with good and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Proteſtants; and vve knovv to whoſe Councils and Advice, and at whoſe door we muſt charge the filling of ſo many Places of Truſt vvith unqualified Perſons. If an E. of <hi>Sunderland</hi> and Lord <hi>Churchil</hi> had not been Miniſters of State and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites then, perhaps the <hi>Leo</hi> had not yet been exchanged for <hi>Kenſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> It is to their faithful Counſels and Influence we owe the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Father <hi>Peters</hi> to the Council Board; the new modelling of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army and Government; the <hi>Magdalen College</hi> Reformation; the Regulation of Corporations; the Cloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, and the Impriſonment and Tryal of the Biſhops: And if ſo, there is a certain Prince who is real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more guilty of thoſe Miſcarriag s than the <hi>Abdicated</hi> Monarch, ſinc he was the main Engine who ſet thoſe noble Lords to work; and I am afraid his Conduct ſince, vvhen exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, will in a great meaſure make good the Charge.</p>
            <p>It's natural enough for a Prince to carry ſome little ſavour to thoſe of his own Religion, and eaſier for a treach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rous Miniſter to trapan him into more Indulgence for them, than the Laws c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll allow; and thoſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47544:9"/>
two Lords being intirely Devoted to the Advancement of the Prince's Deſigns, did imploy their utmoſt Intereſt with the King to bring him into all thoſe Meaſures, which did ſo much favour and precipitate this Revolution. There were ſome faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants who quickly diſcovered the Roguery of this, and ſtoutly made head againſt it; but a blind zeal having betray'd the new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts into thoſe Meaſures, and the time ſerving Courtier being joyned with the Pack, Roguery became too hard for true Honeſty; and yet it was with great difficulty, and match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Importunities, the King was wrought upon to do ſeveral of thoſe Things which were the only impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Errors. It is well known, that it was with no ſmall trouble he was prevailed upon to admit <hi>Peters</hi> to the Council-board. And as to the Regulating of Corporations, the King gave his Opinion againſt it to the very laſt; and I dare appeal to the Earl of <hi>Bathe,</hi> whoſe Teſtimony is not to be ſuſpected by this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if in his acceſs to the King about the Regulations, in thoſe Countries were he was Lieutenant, he did not diſcover the Truth of what I here aſſert, from the King's own Complaints to his Lordſhip, <hi>How greatly he was importuned to give way to thoſe Meaſures, from which in his own Judgment, he was ſo averſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We might have continued Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, in a great meaſure, of the particulars of all this fine Chriſtian Policy, if upon the Revolution theſe honeſt Agents, in ſo good a work, had not (by boaſting of their ſeveral Merits, Diligence and Activity, in betraying an honeſt hearted Prince, and ſo the more Credulous to his own ruin) diſcovered all the Steps of this Intreigue; but in the Opinion of ſome every thing is lawful for the obtaining of a Crown. If it be alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that moſt certainly the Prince never dreamt of the Crown of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> until it was preſented to him, as a reward from a grateful People for their Deliverance; his promiſes of Places at Court, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Forts, before he came from <hi>Holland,</hi> which were only in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſal of the King of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> his impriſonment of the E. of <hi>Fever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham,</hi> who was a publick Meſſenger, and Peer of <hi>England,</hi> and under the Cognizance of none but the King; his impriſoning and baniſhing King <hi>James</hi> from his own Pallace, though acknowleged as the juſt Monarch by his own Declaration; his baniſhing the French Embaſſador out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as ſoon as he came to <hi>London,</hi> and before the Adminiſtration was put into his Hands, by which theſe Kingdoms were ingaged, without their own Conſent, in a War with <hi>France,</hi> without ſo much as any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Entertainment given to their <hi>Abdicated Monarch,</hi> being a conſiderable time before K. <hi>James</hi>'s retreat thither; were direct, poſſitive and moſt Solemn Acts of Sovereignty, before ever the Crown was confer'd upon him; and are ſo many plain and evident Indications of that early Ambition I have charged upon him. And in farther Evidence, that all his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47544:10"/>
Deſigns, from the very firſt, were aimed at the Crown; and the Crown Veſted too with the moſt towring Prerogatives: When the <hi>Convention</hi> was Deliberating, upon ſome future Proviſions, againſt Arbitrary Power, the Prince ſent my Lord <hi>Wharton</hi> to ſeveral Lords, and Mr. <hi>Coulin</hi> to Sir <hi>Edward Seymor,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and other Commoners, to let them known, <hi>That if the Houſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted ſo much upon Limitations, that he would return again, and leave them in the lurch to the Mercy of King</hi> James: So generouſly Tender was this great Deliverer of our Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. As to the Diſpencing Power, aſſumed by King <hi>James,</hi> I do not pretend to juſtifie it. I am heartily ſorry that ſo bad a Meaſure was taken, to carry on and eſtabliſh ſo deſirable and neceſſary a Good and Birth right of Mankind, as <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> which carries its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Beauty and Uſefulneſs, ſo viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſtampt upon it, as could never have failed to obtain an Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Reaſon and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an Engliſh Parliament: But this would have ſo much united the Hearts and Affections of Engliſh Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects with their King, and laid ſuch an invincible rub in the Way of the Prince's ambitious Deſigns, that it became one of the niceſt and moſt ſickliſh Points to manage, the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to ward off, and the moſt dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous and artful part of their Game; there was no downright oppoſing of ſo general and deſirable a Good; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was eaſier to poyſon and divert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> The King was firſt put upon Eſtabliſhing this Liberty by a Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that ſo the Parliament might be prejudiced againſt a Thing, which otherwiſe they would have granted, upon the account of the firſt Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure taken about it; but finding that the general Good and Benefit, which was to be reaped from this Liberty, would have digeſted and ſweetned this Pill; from a pretence of ſaving the King's Honor from a Foyl, and making all ſure, though really with a deſign to ruin Him and baffle the Thing, they put him upon the Regulating and Cloſetting Projects, and upon obliging the Clergy to read his Proclamation for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> from their Pulpits. This did alarm the Biſhops, as was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, and obliged them to think upon Petitioning againſt it; upon which, thoſe <hi>Beautefeux,</hi> being afraid leſt the KING ſhould call in his Proclamation, having always found it hard enough to bring Him to ſuch Methods; they ordered the buſineſs ſo, that the Biſhops were ſo long in preſenting of their Petition to the King, that though their Reaſons had convinced and ſatisfied Him, there was not time enough to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termand his former Orders, though never ſo willing. Upon which they took occaſion to incenſe the King againſt them, as if they had delay'd their Petition ſo long, with deſign to embroyl Him with his People; and ſo they run the Biſhops into the <hi>Tower,</hi> and from thence to the <hi>Barr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the true Hiſtory of the Diſpencing Power, and of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Perſecution, which was ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47544:10"/>
warmly, and bitterly urged againſt the King, as undeniable Proofs that his Inclination to Catholicks was too ſtrong for the Laws. But to ſpeak plain Engliſh, I hope thoſe Stretches, in favour of Catholicks, which were Criminal in King <hi>James,</hi> are not become more Legal and Meritorious in King <hi>William;</hi> the exerciſe of the Diſpencing Power in their favours, I hope, is as much a fault now as ever. The Charge will be denied; but I ſhall make it good when I come to diſcourſe upon the Third Motive to the King's Reſtauration. Are not Catholicks employ'd now in the Army, thô not qualified by Law? It will be alleg'd they are Foreigners; ſo much the worſe; for an Engliſh Catholick will ſtill have ſome regard for the Laws and Liberties of his Countrymen; whereas a mercenary Foreigner is abſolutely at the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of his Maſter. Are not the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks as much Countenanced, and in the exerciſe of as much Liberty for their Religion, as ever? The neceſſity of humouring a Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, which muſt ſupport us, the great Strength of which are Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, may be urged as a very good Reaſon for this; but if we examine it to the bottom, this threatens our Religion more than any Indulgence was granted them by King <hi>James.</hi> When the Catholicks of <hi>England</hi> hold their Liberty merely from the favour of the Proteſtants of <hi>England,</hi> they muſt be thankful for it, and humble under it: but when they come to derive their Favours, Immunities, and Liberty, from the neceſſity of our Circumſtances, and humble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and Deference we muſt pay to Catholick Princes, without whoſe Aſſiſtance and Friendſhip we cannot Subſiſt; their Spirits, Hopes and Haughtineſs, will be enlarged by it: They muſt make grateful acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legements to thoſe Catholick Princes, by whoſe kind Influences they injoy their Liberty. This begets a Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with and Dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Foreign Princes; and we do not know how far, by the Inſtigation of Catholicks here, thoſe Princes may be prevailed upon to improve the neceſſity we have of their Allyance, to the advantage of thoſe of their own Religion amongſt us. The Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> within our remembrance, was the moſt zealous Champions for the Roman Religion, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance of the Catholicks of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> upon that Houſe hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways terrible and troubleſom to this State: And though their Loſſes, and the growth of <hi>France,</hi> hath humbled and levelled all the towring Thoughts and Ambition of that Family, which did ſo much exerciſe both the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Forces of their Neighbours, yet ſince by our Aſſiſtance that Houſe is to recover its Loſſes, and <hi>France</hi> to be reduced within its an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient bounds; with their loſt Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume their old Deſigns: They were but covered up, not extinguiſhed; concealed through Weakneſs, to be diſcovered upon a greater Encreaſe of Strength and Vigour; in which caſe we may come to be whipt for our preſent Politicks</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47544:11"/>May the great God avert thoſe dangers and difficulties which inviron us, and viſibly threaten the Religious and Civil Concerns of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. We have been pulling De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction with both our hands upon our ſelves, and deſperately risking our Religion and Civil Rights with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any neceſſity; and unleſs we repent, and repair theſe Errors, the Puniſhments we deſerve will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overtake us. We have turned away our King, whoſe Right and Title was certain and unqueſtioned, nay we have chaſed him from us with unſpeakable Indignities, upon the Pretence of Errors in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he was put upon by the Artifice of his Enemies, and which he was willing to have repair'd at our own Sight: He courted us by repeated Applications to carve out our own Securities for our Religion and Civil Rights; but we have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately refuſed any Treaty with him. We have ſet our ſelves up for a Mark of Reproach to future Ages, by our fooliſh and invincible Malice and matchleſs Impudence, in <hi>Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Throne</hi> by a pretended <hi>Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> which imports a Voluntary Reſignation; and yet the <hi>Abdicated M narch</hi> never made any, but aſſerts his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itle to this day. We have ground d this <hi>Abdication</hi> upon a wilful <hi>Deſertion</hi> in our Prince, when we forced him away for the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Life; and upon Miſtakes in Government, which he was tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan'd into, and which he was willing to have repaired; but we would not; as if every Error in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had been a Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which neither can be attoned for, nor forgotten. The Injury done to our Sovereign is very viſible from what I have written; and ſo Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ought to be ſpeedily made, notwithſtanding all the Reaſons given by theſe two Pamphleteers againſt it. But before I enter upon anſwering their Objections, I ſhall diſcourſe upon the other three Motives aſſigned for the King's Reſtauration, and make them equally plain with the firſt I have already handled; which will in a great meaſure prevent or take off all Objections can be made.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Motive was the Setling the Government upon its old Baſis; which is viſibly interrupted and quite unhinged by this <hi>Abdication.</hi> We have turned our Hereditary Monarchy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Elective: We have cut the Royal Line, interrupted the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and deſtroyed the juſt Rights of innocent Perſons, upon a pretended <hi>Abdication</hi> which thô well founded, is but perſonal, and cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend d any farther. To this it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by the Author of <hi>The Pretences of the French Invaſion examined,</hi> p 10. l. 1. and downwards, <hi>That the Breach, as to the Perſon of the Reigning King, was made by himſelf, having deſerted; That the Convention did not make, but found the Throne vacant; That in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard there were ſo many clear Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Impoſture of the Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>the Conventi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n applied to the preſent Queen, who was the next and undoubted Heir; and at her Requeſt, a Title was given to her Husband, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for Life, though he was much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47544:11"/>
nearer in Blood than</hi> Henry IV. <hi>and</hi> Henry VII. <hi>ſucceſſively made Kings of</hi> England; <hi>That much greater Breaches have been made, ſince the Conquest, in the Lineal Succeſſion, by depoſing the Reigning King, and ſetting up his Son, or a remoter Perſon, which he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeth an Injury to the King ſo depoſed; and that the ſaving the Succeſſion to the Princeſs of</hi> Denmark <hi>and her Heirs, ſhews how far the Convention was from any ſuch thing as is alledged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By ſuch Reaſonings the Author of this Pamphlet diſcovers but ſmall Knowlege in Hiſtory, and the Affairs of his own Country; little Judgment and Veracity, joyned with a great deal of Diſingenuity and Impudence. How truly the Breach made in our Monarchy, by the <hi>Abdicating</hi> Vote, is to be laid at King <hi>James</hi>'s door, upon the Account of his <hi>Deſertion,</hi> may appear from what I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaid: And though this Author doth very confidently aſſert, That the Throne was void by <hi>Deſertion,</hi> it ſeems the Convention were not of that Opinion, but found it neceſſary to declare it ſo by a Vote, before there was Acceſs to fill it again; and the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rl of <hi>Nottingham</hi> was then quite another Man, and of other Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, than we find him now, as an Author, or Licenſer only. A Regency was not in the leaſt akin to a Vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. But to humour the Author, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there was a Vacancy, either before or after the Vote, which he pleaſeth; a Vacancy in a Monarchy is a certain infallible Mark of its being elective: For in a Hereditary Monarchy, ſuch as this of <hi>England,</hi> upon the Natural, or Civil Death too (if the Author pleaſeth) of the Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Monarch, the Right of the next Succeſſour doth immediately take place; and the People, whether by their Repreſentatives in Parliament, or otherwiſe, do humbly ſubmit to and acknowledge, not declare and authorize, his Native Title. Our Law-books teach us, <hi>That the Kings of</hi> England <hi>can never dye:</hi> The meaning is, That in an Hereditary Monarchy the Throne cannot be without a Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor, were it but for a Moment; ſo that where either there is the leaſt Vacancy, or where the next Poſſeſſor wants a Sentence of the People to give him a Title; that very Sentence, however diſguiſed, is an Election; and together with the preceeding Vacancy, doth certainly and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably ſtamp the Monarchy Elective.</p>
            <p>Is it not highly impudent in this Author to tell us, that there are many clear Indications of the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> being an Impoſture; and, at the ſame time, not to let us know what they are, and upon what Grounds they are ſo clear and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent? Can this Author be ſo vain as to think we muſt take his Word for a Thing upon which ſo much depends; no leſs than the juſtice, or injuſtice of a Sentence, which muſt ſtand the Nation in ſo much Blood and Treaſure, ſo many Perjuries and repeated Acts of Violence and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, to ſupport and maintain? Or doth he therein follow the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in his Declaration? Which tells us of many juſt and viſible Grounds of Suſpicion,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47544:12"/>
that the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> was not Born of the Queen, and refers the Inquiry of that Truth to a free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. King <hi>James</hi> alſo hath made the ſame reference, in a Letter from St. <hi>Germains,</hi> nay deſired the laſt Parliament to look narrowly into that Affair; and yet the Prince hath never to this day deſired the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to fall about this important Search, nor acquainted us with any of thoſe juſt and viſible Grounds of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion. Is it not very ſtrange, That the only plauſible Pretence, in all the Declaration for his undertaking, ſhould be ſo much over-look'd; wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a clear and plain diſcovery of ſuch an infamous Cheat and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, would have fully juſtified the Proceedings of the Convention of Eſtates, the preſent Settlement of the Crown, given us all peace of Conſcience and Satisfaction under it, and would really and truly have <hi>Abd cated</hi> King <hi>James</hi> for ever in the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arts and Affections of every honeſt <hi>Engliſhman?</hi> The Prince in Honor was concerned to have preſs'd it; and the ſupr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>am Senate was oblig'd in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Ju tice to have made a fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Diſcovery of the Truth or Falſ hood o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, eſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cially when they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo much preſs'd and challeng'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it were in the face of the World, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> about it by King <hi>James,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Petitioned ſo to do by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Honor and Quality in <hi>October,</hi> 1690. and which was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into many of the Members Hands; beſides the times and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Affairs were the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſonable for ſuch an Enquiry. It was not to be ſuppoſed, that the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> could either then be bribed or overawed into a partial Teſtimony; and there was all imaginable incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for freedom of Queſtions for confronting the Deponents, and producing Counter Evidences, if there were any ſuch; ſo that the whole Matter might have been laid open and cleared, to the ſatisfaction of all Perſons concerned. The vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating the Honor and Juſtice of the Nation; the quieting of ſo many Peoples Conſciences, who think themſelves bound by their Oaths of Allegiance to the King's next and immediate Heirs; the regard due to an innocent Child, if the Impoſture be not cleared; the ſatisfaction of the Chriſtian World, and the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe Kingdoms from thoſe great Dangers and Confuſions, which are certain and infallible upon Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions, in point of the Royal Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; were great and unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Motives for an Enquiry, nay amounted to the Weight of a Duty due from them to their Conſtituents, themſelves and Poſterity. What can any thinking Man conclude from ſuch a Neglect and Omiſſion, but that the Evidence, for the reality of the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> his Birth, was clear and convincing; and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Evidence, which was pretended againſt it, falſe and forged; that the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> in his Declaration, had rather Studied to amuſe the World with great and ſpecious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, than to ſatisfie them as to the realty and truth of his Grounds; and that the <hi>Convention</hi> and <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:47544:12"/>
have followed the Dictates of Paſſion and Prejudice, more than the Rules of Prudence and Juſtice. It cannot be ſuppoſed they forbore to trace this Impoſture from any ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs to the King's Reputation, which would have been ſo deeply Wounded by a diſcovery of the Cheat. So much time and pains ſpent unſucceſsfully, in laying open the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s pretended Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhews evidently how glad they would have been of any occaſion, or probable pretence, whereby to blacken King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Nation muſt even reſt ſatisfi'd without any further Evidence of this Impoſture, than ſome preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Suſpicions which were both groundleſs, and raiſed induſtriouſly by thoſe publick Agitators for this Revolution: As for Inſtance, The Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> being forced out of the way to the <hi>Bath</hi> at the time of the Queen's Delivery; whereas it is very well known, and can be made appear, by Perſons of undoubted Honor and Integrity, that the King was againſt it, that her Phyſitians in Ordinary were againſt it, and that pains was taken to ſearch about for Phyſitians who would adviſe her going, as expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for her Health; ſo early were they contriving Pretences for this Calumny. But the Prince and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Orange</hi> were all along Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious that the Queen was with Child; and yet no care was taken to ſatisfie them about it. Did they ever acquaint the King with their Suſpicions, and deſire ſome Method might be taken to remove them? And were they refuſed it? This was the proper and uſual way in ſuch Caſes: And ſince it was not taken, there is no ground for Complaint. The King could not dive into Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions; which, in my Conſcience, I am perſuaded they never entertain'd. And laſtly, it is alleged no care was taken to ſatisfie the Nation, who were full of doubts about the reality of his Birth. But why did they doubt? Were any Methods negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, which uſed to be obſerved? Or any Perſons ſecluded, who ought to have been preſent? Did they give any intimation of their Suſpicions by humble Petition or Remonſtrance, and deſire to be ſatisfied about 'em? The Queen had formerly brought forth Children without any preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Jealouſies. Who could foreſee that ſuch a black and helliſh Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would be then invented? Yet the Wiſdom of God Almighty know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how far the Wickedneſs of this Age would extend; and as an earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, I hope, of his good and kind Intentions to this Nation, hath Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntially furniſhed us with a better and more numerous Evidence of the Birth of this Prince, than can be brought for the realty of the Birth of any Prince, or private Perſon in <hi>Europe;</hi> and hath yet fortified and confirmed it by another Conception, and Pregnancy of the Queens, to the Birth of which Child many Perſons of all Qualities have been called, and invited in an extraordinary manner; ſo willing is the King to ſatisfie even our malitious ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47544:13"/>
Complaints. But it ſeems our Rulers have no doubts upon that Head, in which they deſire to be ſatisfied, or find it not for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to have them cleared.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, it is evident that there is a real Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> who muſt be conſidered as ſuch ſo long as the pretended Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture is not cleared to us, and who hath Injuſtice done him by the <hi>Convention of Eſtates;</hi> for though the <hi>Abdicating Vote</hi> were well founded againſt the Father, it was only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal to Him, and cannot reach the Son: In which Caſe, the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Right being only from the Guift and by the Election of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is a manifeſt Breach of the Royal Line, and hath quite altered the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Frame of our Hereditary Monarchy. As to the Title given to the Prince during Life, at her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark,</hi> by the Rules of Succeſſion in an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Monarchy, is unqueſtionably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ex Heir to her Siſter the Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> if ſhe dye without Children: By the Survivancy of Royalty lodged in the Prince, after the Princeſs's Death, there is another manifeſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury done to the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> and her Children; there is another unqueſtionable Breach made upon the Royal Line, and the antient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our Monarchy; and there is a ſecond Election of a Monarch by the Convention, to the Prejudice of the next undoubted Heir, leſt the firſt Inſtance had not made a ſtro g enough Preſident for an Elective Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy for the future. And whereas it is pretended, That the Prince had his Title at the requeſt of the Princeſs, who was the next Heir, and willing to give him Place, where is this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt and Conceſſion of the Princeſs to be ſeen? When was it preſented to the Convention; or where is it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded? But thô it were real, what is that to the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> and her Heirs? Can a Compliment, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> from her ſelf to her Husband, cut off their Rights? Again, is it not evident, That by ſuch a requeſt it's confeſſed the preſent Settlement of the Crown is by the Election and from the Gift of the People; and plainly acknowledged that there is a Right in them to alter the Succeſſion, and make a Breach of the Royal Line at their Pleaſure?</p>
            <p>But it is alledged, We have the practiſe of our Predeceſſors to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant our preſent Meaſures, who have made much greater Breaches in the Lineal Succeſſion, depoſed Kings, and given the Crown to Perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter from the Royal Blood than the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> and that in the Caſes of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. and <hi>Hen.</hi> VII. In this the Author diſcovers himſelf to be ignorant of the Hiſtory and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of his own Country, in miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Caſe of <hi>Hen</hi> IV. in giving us an Inſtance in <hi>Hen.</hi> VII. of a Breach of the Lineal Succeſſion, to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the ſurviving King and next Heir, ſince it is very well known that <hi>Richard</hi> the Uſurper was killed in Battel, and leſt no Heir behind him; and King <hi>Henry</hi> being undoubt d Heir of the Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47544:13"/>
his Marriage with the Heireſs of the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> united the two Roſes, and had an unqueſtionable Title to the Crown, without any Breach in the Lineal Succeſſion: And alſo in omitting to give us the Inſtance of <hi>Edw.</hi> III. which are all the Examples our Hiſtory affordeth, and are very far from making a Precedent in our Caſe. <hi>Edw.</hi> III. was the eldeſt Son, and undoubted and neareſt Heir of the Crown; and thô he mounted the Throne during his Father's Life, yet it was upon his Father's Reſignation: And though he had all the Heat and Ambition of a young Man, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered during his Reign a largeneſs and greatneſs of Soul more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, yet he conſtantly refuſed the Crown, until his Father's Reſignation was obtained. This can be none of thoſe greater Breaches of the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, hinted at by our Author; and doth not at all ſute the Caſe of King <hi>William:</hi> And <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. makes as bad a Precedent for our Practiſe. King <hi>Ri.</hi> II. reſigned in the favour of <hi>Hen.</hi> had no Children to be prejudiced by his Reſignation: King <hi>Henry</hi> was the next Heir, the Pretences of the Houſe of <hi>York</hi> being not then ſet on foot; but that Family acquieſced in his Right as well as the reſt of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: So that our own Hiſtories can as little furniſh us with Examples, to juſtifie our preſent Practiſe, as thoſe of other Nations. If in the Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aſſigned, the horrid Violences of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, the Male Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second and <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, could not in the Opinion of this Author warrant their Dethronnig, from the Character of Injuries done them, he muſt certainly be jeſting all along with us in his Pamphlet, in juſtifying an <hi>Abdication,</hi> for leſs and ſhorter Errors; and the Tory <hi>Nottingham</hi> is forced at laſt to peep out from under his <hi>Republican</hi> Diſguiſe.</p>
            <p>As to the Pretence, <hi>That by ſaving the Succeſſion to the Princeſs of</hi> Denmark <hi>and her Heirs, the Convention hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ſhewn how far they were from deſigning any Alteration in the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or the ancient Conſtitution of our Monarchy;</hi> it is equally weak and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous with any of the reſt; and lays a Foundation for another Election, as it is expreſſed in the Vote: For the Proviſion is not to the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s Heirs ſimply, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor falſly and diſingenuouſly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, but runs thus, <hi>To the Princeſs</hi> Ann <hi>of</hi> Denmark <hi>and the Heirs of her Body;</hi> which failing to the Heirs of the Body of the ſaid K. <hi>William,</hi> which excludes all collateral Pretenders of the <hi>Orleans</hi> and <hi>Palatine</hi> Families, who would have been comprehended under the general Notion of <hi>Heirs.</hi> It was not poſſible for the Wit of Man to contrive a Vote, which in ſo few Words could more viſibly alter the Nature of our <hi>Hereditary Monarchy,</hi> make more and ſtronger Precedents for an Elective, occaſion more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption in the Succeſſion, and lay a better Foundation for the like for the time to come. For in this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence we have a Breach in the Perſon of the reigning King, by the <hi>Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> we have another Breach in the Perſon of the Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> we
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47544:14"/>
have the People conferring the Crown by Election upon the Princeſs of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> to the Prejudice of that Prince his Title; we have a Survivancy of the Government ſettled in the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> by a ſecond Act of this Elective Power of the People, to the prejudice of the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> and her Heirs, which makes a third Breach in the Succeſſion; and laſtly, we have all the Collateral Heirs of this Crown quit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cut off by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale; by which the Monarchy is to b extingu ſhed, or a <hi>Series</hi> of Elective Monarchs buckled upon this Nation, us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trongly as thoſe good Patriots could do it by their Sentence. Let any wiſe and thinking Man judge, if this be not ſuch a palpable and viſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>inging of all the antient Frame and Conſtitution of our glorious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, as deſerves the warmeſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours and moſt diligent Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every honeſt Man, for the ſettling of this our antient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment upon its old <hi>Baſis,</hi> by the Reſtauration of K. <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of <hi>A Letter to a Friend concerning the French Invaſion,</hi> did cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly foreſee theſe Difficulties the former Author had run himſelf into; and being unwilling to ſhipwrack his Reaſon upon ſuch groſs Abſurdities, he broadly hints at <hi>Conquest:</hi> And in this he but ſeconds the Author of the <hi>Anſwer to the Paper delivered by Mr.</hi> Aſhton <hi>at his Execution,</hi> Licenced by a Secretary of State; who boldly, and without Diſguiſe, pleadeth upon that Title. This Plea, though it be not liable to the ſame Abſurdities with the other, yet labours under greater; ſince by one blow, and with one daſh of his Pen, he levels at the Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rights of the Subjects, as well as of the Monarch; and undeavours to extinguiſh the Freedoms of Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as well as the antient Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and certainly to entail upon and place us actually under that Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, the fear of which is the beſt Reaſon they aſſign for reſtraining us from aſſiſting our King in his <hi>Return;</hi> as if ſuch remote fears of Slavery were more dreadful than preſent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, which is the neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <hi>Conqueſt.</hi> Theſe Champions make very bold with their Prince, and wound his Honour and Intereſt deeper than the keeneſt Enemies could do: Such Blunders muſt fall in, when Men reaſon rather from Paſſion than from ſteady and generally received Maxime, and labour to defend a deeply tinctured Republican Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution by Tantivy Monarchical Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
            <p>It is ſtrange to ſee a Man who is indued with a rational Soul, whoſe greateſt Prerogative and Excellency conſiſts in a clear unbyaſſed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Exerciſe of Reaſon, ſo blinded with fooliſh Prejudice, as rather than ſubmit to plain and convincing Truth, chuſe to betake himſelf to this unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable notion of Conqueſt; which is abſolutely inconſiſtent with the Prince's Declaration, deſtroys the Maxims and Grounds, upon which the Convention of Eſtates (from whom the Prince derives his Title) did proceed; overturns the Subjects Claim to Rights and Privileges, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47544:14"/>
pretended care of which is the beſt Support of this Government; brings home to our Fancies and Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the moſt frightful <hi>Ideas,</hi> which a free-born People can form to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of Tyranny and Slavery, with all the terrible and deſolating Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences which attends them; and conſequently lays us under Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, from a due regard to our ſelves and Poſterity, and Duty to our Country, to ſhake off the Yoak with all Speed, though with neverſomuch Hazard and Difficulty.</p>
            <p>The Prince, in his Declaration, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an Enumeration of Grievances, aſſures us <hi>He came for no other Deſign, than to have a free and full Parliament aſſembled, and the Elections made and returned according to the antient forms; and that the Members of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould meet and ſit in full freedom, until ſuch Laws be prepared, as the two Houſes ſhould concur in, and find neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for Maintenance of the Proteſtant Religion, and ſecuring the Peace, Honour and Safety, of this Nation; that there may be no more Danger of falling at any time under</hi> Arbitrary Government; <hi>and that he had nothing before his Eyes, in this Undertaking, but the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, the Covering of all Men from Perſecutions for their Conſciences, and the ſecuring to the whole Nation the free Enjoyment of all their Laws, Rights and Liberties, under a juſt and legal Government.</hi> For the accompliſhing of which, ſince he had only brought a Force with him, for defending his Perſon, <hi>againſt the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of Evil Counſellors,</hi> all the Peers of this Realm, Lieutenants, Deputy-Lieutenants, and others of all Ranks and Degrees, are invited to aſſiſt him againſt all who ſhall endeavour to oppoſe the redreſſing of Violences done to the Conſtitution of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Government. Theſe Pretences can never be adjuſted to the Notion and Title of <hi>Conqueſt.</hi> The Nobility, Gentry, and Commons of this Realm, acting in a free and legal Parliament, for the ſecuring of their Laws, Rights and Liberties, under a juſt and legal Government, neither can nor will ever deſign it.</p>
            <p>I will charitably ſuppoſe the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Eſtates, and their Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuents, did believe they had valuable Rights and Privileges, their Religion, Liberties and Properties, which were derived and ſecured unto them from poſitive Statutes and Laws of the Land, as well as from the Dictates of Nature and <hi>Original Contract;</hi> that thoſe Rights and Privileges were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded, and in danger to be loſt; which made them run into that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Defection, and make a Preſent of the Crown to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as the only expedient they could then think of. So long as the Prince's Title runs in this Channel, they are at Liberty, when they pleaſe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view thoſe Meaſures, examine the Grounds, and upon a Rectification of their Judgments, and Conviction that their beloved Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges may be better ſecured under their antient Monarch, to betake themſelves again unto him. <hi>Sublata cauſa, tollitur effectus.</hi> Or they may enquire into the Conduct and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Prince, whether it Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47544:15"/>
with the <hi>Original Contract</hi> they made with him; whether their <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Privileges</hi> have been entirely preſerved; and if they can diſcover any bad Influences or Aſpect towards <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> then to make a Sacrifice of the Workmanſhip of their own Hands to a freſh Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe Sacred and Venerable Rights, by the Maxims of this laſt Revolution; <hi>The Interest of the People is paramount to that of the Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if our <hi>Conqueſt</hi> take place, then <hi>Adieu</hi> to <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Privileges, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property.</hi> The old muſty Statute Books and Records of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter hall</hi> and the <hi>Tower,</hi> may be committed to the Flames, as ſo much waſte Paper: His Will and Pleaſure muſt be the Law whereby we are governed; our Liberties muſt lie at the Mercy of his Miniſters; and our Properties muſt be committed to the Stewardſhip of his Soldiers. Let us examine the Condition of Conquered People and Provinces, from antient and modern Hiſtory. Their old Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Laws and Cuſtoms, which they had been inured to from their Infancy, recommended and endeared to them by long Uſe and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, muſt be ſwept off the Stage; ſtrange Orders, ſtrange Cuſtoms, ſtrange Miniſters, muſt take their place: Our Perſons, our Liberty, our Eſtates, and all our moſt valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earthly Enjoyments, muſt lie at the Mercy, Pleaſure, and Will, of the <hi>Conqueror:</hi> Induſtry and Virtue will vaniſh, there being no Reward for them; for a <hi>Conquered People</hi> muſt aſpire no higher, than to learn to obey ſubmiſſively, and to eat the Bread of Tribulation and Affliction with Patience: The care and deſire of Poſterity will languiſh; being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to beget Children, to become Slaves and miſerable as our ſelves. The <hi>Indian</hi> Women ſtrangled their own Children, after their Birth, that they might not become Servants to the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Severities will be found nothing ſhort, upon the Record of Hiſtory, of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The Annals of all Nations can furniſh us with dreadful Inſtances of the unſpeakable Miſeries of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered People:</hi> We may find thoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the Calamities of that Condition, which would make us embrace Death for a Favour, and be able to ſink us into utter De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, unleſs at the ſame time theſe very Hiſtories had given us a view of the ſtrenuous and ſucceſsful Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of thoſe generous and worthy Spirits, who have deſpiſed Dangers, Difficulties, Torments, and Death it ſelf, for the Reſcue and Deliverance of their Country and fellow Subjects. The greater and more terrible the Dangers were, the more vigorouſly and undauntedly did they court them, when they were in purſuit of ſo glorious a Quarry. The Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of Conquered Nations for the Recovery of their loſt Liberties, ſtand faireſt upon the Records of Fame, and are handed down to us with the greateſt Exactneſs and <hi>Encomiums;</hi> as if our Anceſtors had judged it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and all Writers had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together to rouze up, when Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion called for it, that deſire of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47544:15"/>
Liberty, which was born with us. If Conqueſt muſt be forced upon us as our preſent Lot; I hope all true Engliſhmen now will diſcover as great a Senſe, as any upon Record of a vindicative Duty to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and love for their Liberties, be as tender and careful to tranſmit them ſafe and ſound to their Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as their Anceſtors have been vigilant and active in handing them down to them; that they will be no leſs careful of the ancient Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Monarchy of this Nation, than of their own particular Rights; ſince every blow which reaches the one, muſt certainly wound and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the other; and that it ſhall be impoſſible to make the Engliſh a Conquered People, becauſe they will generally chuſe not to be, rather than to be Slaves.</p>
            <p>It may be alledged, that all that I have ſaid upon Conqueſt might have been forborn, ſince the King ſets up for no ſuch Title; perhaps it is not ſeaſonable to do it: But to have Conqueſt ſo publickly pleaded for in Pamphlets, Written or Licenſed by <hi>Secretaries of State,</hi> and that without any Check or Puniſhment from the Prince is very ſuſpicious, eſpecially if upon Examination of thoſe Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which we ſuffer under the preſent King, we ſhall find his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct ſmell Rank that way. If we be treated as a Conquered People, the Miſery is ſtill the ſame, or rather greater; though the Prince who deals ſo by us ſhould be called a Reformer.</p>
            <p>It being made evident and plain, That King <hi>James</hi> was highly injur'd, and the antient Government quite unhinged, by the Sentence of <hi>Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> and our late Meaſures. I come next to examine how exactly the Prince hath fulfilled, and made good unto us the pretended Ends and Deſigns of his Declaration; how well he hath kept the <hi>Original Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract</hi> we made with him; and what benefit we may expect to reap for the future by this <hi>Revolution.</hi> I ſhall take his Conduct in both Kingdoms joyntly under Conſideration, ſince he hath not only united them in the ſame Declaration, but likewiſe iſſu'd out a Declaration apart for <hi>Scotland;</hi> intimating thereby, <hi>That the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in that Kingdom were more weighty and numerous than here, and that the Arbitrary Deſigns of our Prince did always firſt commence there, to make a Precedent for this Kingdom; and that the Conduct and Poſture of Affairs there, did always certainly Prognoſticate to the curious Obſerver, what was deſigned to be Copied and Executed here.</hi> I do not pretend to give a particular detail of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Adminiſtration in that Kingdom; but there are ſome conſiderable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors have been acted there which have made a Noiſe, and rais'd ſuch publick Complaints there, as hath convey'd the Knowledge of them here to us.</p>
            <p>The aſſuming a Power of Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with the due Execution of Laws, enacted by King and Parliament for Security of Religion, Liberty, and Happineſs of the Subject, is much urged againſt King <hi>James,</hi> as a great
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47544:16"/>
Motive to the Prince's undertaking. A Diſpenſing Power aſſumed by any Prince, doth fatally threaten the Liberties of a People where it is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, and makes them Tenants at Will for thoſe Privileges which the Laws of the Land hath given them a Freehold in. This is really ſuch an important Point, and of ſuch Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence for the Subject to have been cleared, that it was indiſpenſably the Duty of a Reforming Prince, Convention of Eſtates, and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to have decided this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, and placed ſuch Marks and Boundaries for the future, ſo plain and obvious both to Prince and People, that each might have known their particular Rights, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves for the future ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. But our Parliaments have thought fit to leave it where they found it, dark and undecided to this day; and the Prince hath diſcovered he was well enough pleaſed with this Omiſſion, by taking as large and broad Steps that way, as any can be charged upon King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Iriſh Treaty furniſheth us with a convincing Proof of this; where ſuch Indulgences were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed unto them ſolely and ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y by his own Authority, with relation to the exerciſe of their Religion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their Arms, diſpenſation from Oaths, and ſecurity againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſuits for their Plunderings; as were directly contrary to the Laws of the Land, the Safety, Rights, and Privileges of the Proteſtant Subjects of that Kingdom. This Treaty, I do acknowledge, was afterwards ratified by Parliament; but though in ſome Caſes the Authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament may give a legal Being for the future, yet that new Life com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menceth only from the date of their Sanction, and doth not juſtifie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Errors; and the many Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties which aroſe in both Houſes about the Ratification, was a clear <hi>Innuendo</hi> how dangerous and illegal they judg'd the Treaty to be. How ſtrangely are we altered? King <hi>James</hi>'s exerciſe of this Diſpenſing Power, could neither be forgotten nor attoned for; but King <hi>William</hi>'s ſtretch that way, ſhall obtain a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary Approbation; ſuch is the Juſtice and unbyaſſed Integrity of theſe Times.</p>
            <p>But we need not look ſo far as <hi>Ireland</hi> for Inſtances: We have our perſonal Liberties ſecured to us by poſitive and expreſs Statutes, and Methods appointed by our Law, whereby to recover our Liberties when loſt, with ſuch ſevere Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions againſt thoſe who obſtruct the due courſe of Law in obtaining of our Freedom, with ſuch great and conſiderable Damages appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that caſe, as plainly enough Points out unto us the Value and Worth of this true Engliſh Privilege. It is the choiſeſt piece of our <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and <hi>Original Contract;</hi> and, for my part, I ſhould much rather allow a Prince to diſpence with Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Statutes, and iſſue out a Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation for Liberty of Conſcience, than to ſport himſelf at Pleaſure with my perſonal Freedom; without
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47544:16"/>
which there can be no reliſh in any other Enjoyment; and yet there never was a Reign wherein our Birth-right in this hath been more abuſed, ſpoiled, and broken in upon. The Engliſh Subjects have been put into Proclamations, and clapt into Priſons for High Treaſon, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the benefit of their <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> though there was no Information upon Oath againſt them, according as the Law appoints to warrant ſuch a Procedure: Nay ſo groſly, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and impudently, have our publick Miniſters affronted the Laws upon this Head, that they have found themſelves obliged to apply to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for Pardon: For we have found out a new Trick in this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and reforming Age, firſt to act all imaginable Violences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the beſt and choiſeſt of our Laws, and than to obtain either a Ratification or Pardon in Parliament; whereby they have ſtruck our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Conſtitution, and the Liberty of the Subject, Dead at one Blow, by Debauching our Parliaments into a Confederacy againſt, (in place of Protecting,) the Liberties of the People, and ſo making the Nation as it were <hi>Felo de ſe.</hi> No period of Hiſtory doth furniſh us with ſuch wholeſale Merchants for our beſt and moſt valuable Rights; neither do we know when this Trade ſhall be at an end, or when our Rulers will be weary of Tricking us out of our Liberties. We have a freſh Inſtance of late of the Knowledge and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our <hi>Judges:</hi> When the Earls of <hi>Huntington, Midleton,</hi> and others moved at the <hi>Barr</hi> for their <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> there was no Information upon Oath againſt them to warrant a refuſal; otherways to be ſure we ſhould have heard of it: But <hi>Aaron Smith</hi> muſt make Affidavit that they had Evidence for the High Treaſon charged againſt them, which could not be got ready; and ſo by his Liberty and Freedom of Conſcience, ſave in ſome meaſure the Credit of the Court: By this fine new Knack, they were all remitted back to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon again. Such <hi>Judges</hi> may at laſt come to be fit enough for the <hi>Bench</hi> even under a Conqueſt; but in the mean time all ſuch Expedients, which are not warranted from the Statutes, do rather prove the Injuſtice of the Court, than fulfil the Law; and however it may be Gilded, we cannot but ſee and feel the bitter Pill we muſt ſwallow.</p>
            <p>Was not the <hi>Habeas Corpus Act</hi> ſuſpended for many Months? It's true this was done by Parliament; but ſo much the worſe, if our own Delegates, in whoſe Hands we truſt the care, but not the intire ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our Liberties, make a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of that which is not in their Power, to the Ambition or Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of any Prince. Parliaments can no more juſtly over-turn Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than the Prince can. Such Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges as are derived from King and Parliament, upon the account of the Subjects Temporary Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, are truſted to the review of the ſame Court; but theſe Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Privileges, which are the Birth-right of Nations, and derived
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47544:17"/>
Originally from the Laws of Nature it ſelf; ſuch as the Freedom of our Perſons, and Dominion over our Properties, fall only under the Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of Parliaments, for their better Eſtabliſhment againſt ſuch Breaches, as the depraved Nature of Princes and their Miniſters will be making upon them.</p>
            <p>The Nature and Deſign of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, hath occaſioned a partial Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of theſe two great native Privileges to the ſafety of that Body Politick, by puniſhing of Crimes; and to the ſupport of it, by Taxes, which we grant our ſelves; but in no Conſtruction of Reaſon, Senſe, or Juſtice, can Delegates be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to be impowered, to make an intire ſurrender of thoſe Rights into the Hands of any Prince, were it but for a moment. It may be alledged, That the ſafety and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Government put our <hi>Rulers</hi> upon ſuch extraordinary Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. If reaſons and pretences of State (the Secrets of which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways locked up in the Prince his Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt) can apoligize for ſuch bold Strok s, againſt our moſt Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Privi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eges and Laws; Where is there any Right or Immunity, which we can call our own, or be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſured off? Since ſuch pretences ſhall never be wanting to entitle the Prince to an abſolute Dominion over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Property, as well as over our Liberty; ſince the laſt is more valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able than the firſt; Why may not Reaſons of State, as juſtly render him Maſter of the one as of the other?</p>
            <p>If it was to preſerve our Liberties from the inſults of King <hi>James,</hi> we placed the Prince upon the Throne, we have certainly either miſtaken the Diſeaſe or the Cure; ſince he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be preſerved upon it at a chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per rate, than a Sacrifice of what we intended to preſerve, we are to learn nothing from this Revolution, but a ſurer and more infallible way of enſlaving the Subject. King <hi>James</hi> never dreamt of ſuch a Method. An <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament was hitherto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed a Court inſeparable from the true Intereſt of <hi>Engliſhmen;</hi> but a little more Training under ſo good a Maſter may make them change Principles, and become in time as complacent and good natur'd as ever the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Swediſh</hi> States were. Nothing, it ſeems, in Gratitude, can be refuſed to our <hi>Deliverer.</hi> But thô Gratitude be a Virtue, it ought to have its Bounds, leſt it run us farther than deſigned or intended at firſt, even to the deſtruction of thoſe Rights, for the Preſervation of which we deſire to appear ſo grateful. The King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> in our time, by the Merit of ſome Actions performed for his People, and during their firſt Raptures of gratitude for it, ſound the way to Enſlave them, by chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging an Elective and Limited, into an Hereditary and Deſpotick Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</p>
            <p>The admitting of unqualified Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons into Places of Employment, and the erecting the High-Commiſſion-Court, were thought great Crimes in King <hi>James,</hi> and mighty Errors in Government; and yet the firſt is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47544:17"/>
as frequently practiſed in the Army as ever; and how much further the Prince's dependance upon Popiſh Confederates may lead him in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Catholicks, muſt be owing to their Moderation; for we lie at their Mercy upon that head, and may come to be made ſenſible, that our Foreign Allyances may prove as troubleſome and uneaſie to us, in favour of Papiſts, as King <hi>James</hi>'s Religion was: And as to the laſt, the Prince muſt either look upon that Court to be no Crime, or by favouring the moſt active Members in it, he muſt deſtroy and invert that old Engliſh Maxim, <hi>That our Kings can neither Err, nor be Puniſhed; but that evil Counſellors are liable to both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The turning out the Fellows of <hi>Magdalen College</hi> from their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, contrary to that Proviſion in <hi>Magna Charta, That no Man ſhould loſe his Life or Goods, but by the Law of the Land,</hi> is not to be juſtified; and yet falls much ſhort of the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting People to death, under this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by Martial Law, before it was Enacted. Few Men will ever ſcruple to ſecure their Lives, with the loſs of their Places. The <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> and <hi>Regulation Projects,</hi> were much to be complained of; but we may very eaſily imagine to whoſe Practiſes they were owing, by the Countenance and Preferments the Authors and Promoters of thoſe Councils received from this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; neither can the <hi>Quo Warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toing</hi> of <hi>Charters</hi> be ſo illegal, as the Declaration would make us believe; ſince King <hi>William</hi> himſelf treads in the ſame Path, by impoſing a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor upon <hi>New England,</hi> upon the <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> Foot, contrary to the Opinion of his Privy-Council.</p>
            <p>Whereas by the Declaration, the ſlighting and rejecting of Petitions delivered by Subjects, with Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Reſpect, is conſidered as a high Strain of abſolute Power; yet when the People of <hi>Scotland</hi> had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to themſelves the Privilege of Petitioning, by their claim of Rights; and in purſuance, and by virtue of that Privilege, the greateſt part of that Parliament, which placed the Crown upon his Head, had humbly addreſſed unto the preſent King for his aſſent to ſome Votes, which they had paſſed for Eſtabliſhing of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Liberty, and which were agreeable to their antient Laws and Privileges, they were ſcornfully and diſdainfully refuſed and rejected. If by the Declaration it was a fault to treat a Peer of <hi>England</hi> as a <hi>Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> for aſſerting that the Subjects were not bound to obey a Popiſh Juſtice of Peace; it cannot be a piece of Juſtice in King <hi>William</hi> to paſs a Sentence of Baniſhment upon the Earl of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> who is a Peer of <hi>England,</hi> within theſe few Weeks, without ſo much as alleging a Crime againſt him.</p>
            <p>Since by the Declaration, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging People to deliver their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before hand, as to the repealing the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and the turning out of Employments ſuch as would not promiſe luſtily, is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as ſo fowl a piece of Collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47544:18"/>
The Cloſetting of Members of Parliament now, to pre-engage their Votes in Affairs depending be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and the Diſgraces which ſome obſtinate Perſons fell under upon it, ſhould have been forborn, unleſs King <hi>William</hi> be diſſatisfied with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and the Rules and Maxims therein Eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>According to the Scottiſh Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the appointing of Judges in an unuſual manner, and giving 'em Commiſſions, which were not to continue during Life, or good Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, was highly illegal; yet K. <hi>William,</hi> after he got the Crown, found he was miſtaken in that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, and nominated the whole Bench, without ſubjecting them to a Tryal and Approbation of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according as Law and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom required; did not think fit to continue their Commiſſions during Life or good Behaviour; and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them a Lord Preſident, thô by expreſs Statute he was to be ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Bench.</p>
            <p>By the Declaration, the impoſing of Bonds upon whole Counties with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Act of Parliament, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of free Quarters to the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, are declared to be high and intollerable Stretches of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: The ſame hath been practiſed in this Government, with greater Confidence, leſs Compaſſion, and other aggravating Circumſtances. Bonds have been impoſed by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Council, without Warrant of Parliament, as may appear from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> publick Proclamations; and many Thouſands of Soldiers have been maintained upon free Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and for many Months together countenanced and abetted in it by the Government; and the Funds for reimburſing the Countrey, which were appointed by <hi>Parliament,</hi> have been otherways diverted.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſionating the Officers of the Army, to ſit as Judges upon the Lives and Eſtates of the Subjects, and the putting People to death without a legal Tryal, Jury, and Record; were complained of in the Declaration; were thought good Reaſons for Fore-faulting of K. <hi>J.</hi> and were provided againſt upon this laſt Setlement of the Crown: And yet both the caution given by the Sentence againſt K. <hi>J.</hi> and the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Proviſion made by the <hi>Eſtates,</hi> prove to weak to reſtrain this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment from practiſing the ſame things, by ordering and impower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Colonel <hi>Hill,</hi> and Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>Hamilton,</hi> to put <hi>Glencou</hi> and all the Males of his <hi>Clan,</hi> under Seventy, to death; which was partly executed upon them, without any legal Tryal, Jury, or Record. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can their former Enmity, and oppoſition to the Government, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh any Apology for ſo barbarous a Murther, ſince they had all either actually taken the benefit of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity then granted, and ſo were Pardoned, or had Protections in their <hi>Pockets,</hi> which put them under the immediate care and ſafeguard of the Government. It may puſle the beſt Heads to find out the reaſon why <hi>Iriſh Papiſts,</hi> though ſtated Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47544:18"/>
ſhould be indulged to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of our Laws and Rights; and yet <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> though formerly Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, barbarouſly Maſſacred, when indemnify'd and under protection; unleſs K. <hi>W.</hi> be reſolved, from the Obligations he is under, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference he muſt pay to the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Princes,</hi> to imbrace every oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of deſtroying the one, and cheriſhing the other.</p>
            <p>By the Declaration we are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That the Prince will concur in every thing that may procure the Peace and Happineſs of theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and which a free and lawful Parliament ſhall determine; and yet how many neceſſary and uſeful Bills, for the Happineſs of the Nation, have been ſtifled by the Intereſt, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treigues, and Sollicitations of the King himſelf, his Miniſters and Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers; and the Royal Aſſent refuſed to many Bills in our Neighbouring Kingdom: And in this to the Bill about <hi>Judges,</hi> which was thought ſo neceſſary an expedient for the Eſtabliſhing of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and to cut off their ſervile Dependance upon the Court, which was charged as ſuch a blemiſh upon the <hi>Judges</hi> in K. <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, and was always look'd upon as dangerous to the <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the Engliſh Subjects.</p>
            <p>We were aſſured that the only deſign of the Prince's Undertaking, was, <hi>The preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, the covering all Men from Perſecution for their Conſciences, and the ſecuring to the whole Nation the free injoyment of all their Laws, Rights and Liberties, under a juſt and legal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> How well and truly he hath confined himſelf within theſe Limits, and other Bounds he preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to himſelf in his Declaration, may partly appear from what hath been ſaid; and ſhall yet be made more clear and evident by a true and impartial Enquiry into his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and ſome conſiderable Stretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es which have been made in Points not glanced at by the Declaration, becauſe they were Strains of Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and Deſpotick Power, which K. <hi>James</hi>'s Reign did not furniſh us with any Inſtances of the like.</p>
            <p>The Power of impoſing Taxes is unqueſtionably lodg'd in Parliament; and the People of this Iſland have a natural Right unto, and Dominion over their Properties; and the Prince cannot ſhare with them in it, in whole, or in part; except in ſo far as they conſent to it themſelves, by their Repreſentatives in Parliament: And our Parliaments, though abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly liberal in other reſpects, have never indulged the leaſt Liberty to our Monarchs on that head; being ſo far tight to their Truſt; and their Conſtituents Intereſt: And the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of both Kingdoms judg'd it neceſſary, upon the preſent Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Crown, to aſſert the Peoples Right in it; and plainly to expreſs it as one of the Conditions of that Settlement. And yet the Privy Council of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> have openly and avowedly, in Contempt of the antient Laws and <hi>late Original Contract,</hi> by their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Proclamations, commanded and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47544:19"/>
appointed, under the ſevereſt Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the Subjects of that Kingdom, at their own Charge and Expence, to furniſh a great number of Horſes for the uſe and ſervice of the Army; and for carrying Ammunition and Proviſion of Victuals, with Men to attend the ſaid Horſes: And I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, That when upon cool and ſecond Thoughts the Council, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what they had done, how il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal it was, and the danger they had run themſelves into by it, thought fit to apply unto the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for an Approbation, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed them.</p>
            <p>Extravagant Bail was complained of, and provided againſt by the States of both Kingdoms; and yet it is dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and frequently impoſed, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted many times far above the Value of their Eſtates.</p>
            <p>The Freedom of Elections to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, from the Bribes and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Court and Courtiers, was expreſly conditioned by the States of both Kingdoms, upon their Tender of the Crown. How well that is kept and obſerved, may appear from the bare faced and open Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made to Counties, Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and particular Electors, for the Choice of ſuch and ſuch Perſons, with Threats and promiſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Nay, I have known Three thouſand Pounds expended for ſecret Service, to prevent the Election of a Perſon who had been eminently Serviceable to this Government, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me he was found tighter to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntereſt of his Country, than to the Court<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for there never was a Reign wherein the Intereſt of King and People are more confidently ſtated as contradiſtinct, than in this, though it be only the Conſent and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Intereſt of the People, gives Birth, Riſe, and Title to it.</p>
            <p>The frequency of Parliaments, for redreſſing of Grievances; the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending, ſtrengthning, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Laws, with all Freedom of Speech and Debates in them, was inſiſted upon and fundamentally e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by the States of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, when they elected their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſties to the Throne How well this is obſerved and made good to both Kingdoms, is obvious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. It is not for redreſſing of Grievances, amending or preſerving the Laws, they are aſſembled; but for giving of Money. The craving Neceſſities of the State, the preſſing Circumſtances of the Conſederates and foreign Affairs, the early Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations of the French King, an honourable Peace, the Good of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and Fears of King <hi>James;</hi> are become the cruel and everlaſting Topicks, the common and ordinary Stale, whereby the true Intent of Parliaments is baffled, and the Money buſineſs quickened and finiſhed. The laſt is now ſo much the buſineſs of Parliaments, and the firit ſo little, that it is an equal Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that this Court may come at laſt to plead <hi>Preſcription</hi> againſt <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,</hi> as to any other buſineſs but Money-bills.</p>
            <p>As to freedom of Speech and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, though there be none queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned for it, yet Members are ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47544:19"/>
Diſcouraged and Frowned upon at Court, Diſgraced and turn'd out of Employments, whenever they launch out into an enquiry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Grievances, or the preſent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration: And upon the other hand, the Places of Honor and Truſt, and the Money of the Nation, are ſo openly and viſibly employed for debauching of Members from a ſenſe and feeling of the true Intereſt of the People, and for diveſting them of all the publick and generous Notions, Zeal, unwearied and bold Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for the Rights and Privileges of the Subject, the joynt Good and Intereſt of King and Kingdom, which hath been hitherto ſo much the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Entertainment of brave <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Spirits in our <hi>Parliaments;</hi> that this native and neceſſary Freedom of Speech and Debates, is more viſibly threatned, and more effectually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, than ever could have been done by Force, Sentence, or Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment. We are ſooner wheed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with falſe, if gilded, <hi>Pretences,</hi> than hectored or huffed into a Court Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, was there ever a Reign, wherein the plunderings and Free qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>terings of Soldiers was more counteranced, and the People more grievouſly oppreſſed by them, than in this? The Complaints of <hi>Scotland</hi> upon that head already hinted at, the irregular and unheard of Abuſes and Miſcarriages of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, the Deſolations brought upon that miſerable Kingdom by them, and the daily Inſtances we mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t with of that nature in this Kingdom, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing and undeniable Evidences of the Truth of it. Nay, to ſuch a paſs is it already come, that when a Secretary of State was applied unto, by perſons injured, who were intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Intereſt of the Government, and preſented by the Knight of the Shire with Complaints againſt the Abuſes and free Quartering of Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; they were ſcornfully rejected with this Anſwer, <hi>That Men and Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes muſt eat:</hi> Meaning, no doubt, that ſince the Taxes deſigned by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for that end, were neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be applied unto the uſe of the Conſederates, the people muſt be doubly burdened for the Subſiſtence of the Troops. Such brave Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians are our preſent Rulers become of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties.</p>
            <p>Here we have a ſad but true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of our Miſeries; only it is not full and compleat. The preſent Adminiſtration can furniſh us with a great many more Inſtances: But I have confined my ſelf to a Dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of thoſe groſſer Errors, which viſibly infringed the Pretences of the Prince's Declaration, and the <hi>Petition of Rights;</hi> the ſecuring and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of which, was the Reaſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly aſſigned for his Election into the Throne. If in the Infancy of his Government, when his ſenſe of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for the Gift of Three Crowns, if ever, muſt be freſh in his Memory: when the Hearts and Hands, as well as the Purſes of the People, were neceſſary for his Support; when his Honour as well as Intereſt called for a different Conduct, he run ſo warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into ſuch Meaſures: what muſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47544:20"/>
we feel, when he comes to ſit ſure and be fixt upon his Throne?</p>
            <p>We may certainly conclude upon the Inclinations and future Deſigns of a Prince, by his preceeding Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and the choice of his Miniſters; and from both theſe Reflections, in the preſent Caſe, we have but a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy View of our future Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Are not thoſe very Men, who in both Kingdoms were the Authors, Contrivers, and Actors of the moſt Arbitrary and grievous Proceedings, which were complained of, during the Reigns of our two laſt Monarchs, become the Miniſters, the Darlings, the Favourites of this Reign? Have they changed their Principles and Maxims? The former Inſtances, in which they have their ſhare, may convince us to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Is it to be imagined that a Prince, who ſignalized his Entry upon the Stage of publick Affairs with a breach of the moſt ſolemn Oaths to the contrary, the Deſtruction of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of his Native Country, and by graſping at a Power which the Nature, Law, and Conſtitutions of that Government denied to his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter in it; will be more tender of his Oaths to us, and of our Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution? His paſt Conduct may clear it up unto us; we are Strangers to him, and he to us; his Affections, as well as his Birth, are foreign; he diſtruſts and deſpiſeth us, as treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to our former King; He may <hi>love the Treaſon, but hates the Traytors.</hi> It is not a ſingle Crime can entitle us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Favour; it is by a Sacrifice if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of King and Country we can touch his heart; it is only by this double Treaſon we can get into his Confidence. The Fate and Diſgrace of thoſe Perſons, who upon this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution frankly ſacrificed the firſt, but knew not how to ſubdue their Scruples as to the laſt, may ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prove this Truth. We have none but our ſelves to blame for this Miſchief: By our <hi>Abdicating</hi> Vote, and ſubſequent Meaſures, our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, juſt, and legal Government, is deſtroyed and overturned; and in ſo doing, we have diſingaged him from the Promiſes he made in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, ſince it was only <hi>under a just and legal Government</hi> that we were aſſured of his Endeavours to preſerve our Laws, Rights, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties. Let us yet a little farther examine the Benefits we ſhall reap from this Revolution, the Means we have to ſupport it, and what will probably be the Iſſue of all theſe great Tranſactions.</p>
            <p>The malignant aſpect of our late Meaſures, towards our beloved Rights and Privileges, ſeems to be pretty well cleared already, and ſcarce admits of an aggravating Thought more; unleſs we conſider that we are like to pay the Price of a perfect and laſting Cure, for down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Poyſon and a mortal conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Feavor: But perhaps this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Prince, by his Conqueſts and admirable Conduct, will raiſe the Military Glory of this Nation ſo high, and enlarge her Territories and Command ſo far, as ſhall quite darken and eclipſe the Luſtre and Fame of our greateſt and moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47544:20"/>
Kings; and thereby allevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, or quite bury our Senſe and Feeling of paſt, preſent, and future Miſeries. If the <hi>Lawrels</hi> and <hi>Conqueſts</hi> of a Monarch, which are firſt drench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Tears, and are founded upon the Slavery of the People, can atone for ſuch Miſeries, the <hi>French</hi> at this Day would be the happieſt People in <hi>Europe.</hi> This will not paſs upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, who obſerve from their Hiſtories, that the moſt Victorious of their Monarchs have always been moſt render and careful of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; and I am afraid that even this faint Comfort ſhall not be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded us. What reaſon have we to expect, that by the Conduct and Military Knowledge of a Prince, (againſt whom the Naked and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſciplined <hi>Iriſh</hi> made Head for three Campaigns together,) we ſhall be able to gain Troops and Provinces, from the more Numerous, better Diſciplined, and Conducted Troops of <hi>France?</hi> For though the Author of <hi>A Letter to a Friend concerning a</hi> French <hi>Invaſion</hi> flatters us, with our Victories over the <hi>French</hi> at the <hi>Boyn, Athlone, Agrim,</hi> and <hi>Limrick,</hi> and from thence foretels our Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in <hi>Flanders;</hi> they were ſtill but Undiſciplined <hi>Iriſh</hi> we ſubdued, with difficulty enough in ſome of thoſe Places; and our Victories over the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> or <hi>Flanders,</hi> have not as yet burdened our <hi>Gazettes.</hi> We have already expended many Millions of Morey, and loſt many Thouſands of Men, and have nothing in return for all this Conſumption of Blood and Treaſure, but the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of <hi>Ireland;</hi> which vigorous and early Meaſures could have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured unto us at the begining, and prevented the utter Ruin and Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of that Countrey; and our late Victory at Sea over the <hi>French,</hi> to comfort us for our two former Diſgraces at <hi>Bantry</hi> and <hi>Beachy,</hi> the ſhameful loſs of many of our Navy Royal to the Enemy, the ſeizure of ſo many Hundreds of our Merchant Ships, and our Misfortunes in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:</hi> Some of our former Princes, with a far leſs Expence of Men and Money, when Affairs were managed with true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Councils, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, have ſubdued whole Provinces, and given Law to <hi>Europe.</hi> But we go now upon Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and are governed by Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which are Calculated rather for the Intereſt of Foreign Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Princes, than adjuſted to the Honor, Profit, and Good of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> This Confederacy hath coſt us already a great deal of Money; and it's plain, that the particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, Ambition, and Pretences of theſe Foreign Princes gave Birth to the Prince's Undertaking, rather than any kind regard to our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Rights and Liberties. It is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant enough to imagine that the <hi>Pope,</hi> the Fathers of the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> and the Authors of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> and <hi>Piedm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntiſh Perſecutions,</hi> againſt thoſe of our Religion, ſhould be ſo concerned to eſtabliſh the Proteſtant Belief amongſt us; and that thoſe Foreign Princes, who have extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the leaſt ſhadow of Liberty and Property in their own Dominions,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47544:21"/>
have ſuch pangs of Conſcience, and tender Regard for our expiring Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties. They wanted our Money and our Troops, to carry on their ſeveral Pretences; and if they could be ſtill ſure of Feaſting, and making War at our Expence, the Favour would be as acceptable from the Hands of King <hi>James,</hi> as from the Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> But the Prince who muſt ſtand equally obliged to them for his mounting the Throne, and ſupport in it, was judged a fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Inſtrument, more humble, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and active, for emptying the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Treaſures i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Dutch</hi> Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, than ever they could expect from our Native King, whom they were afraid would be found m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re ſteady to a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt, than to gratifie their un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atiable and boundleſs Pretences.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> was a good Husband of his Treaſure, and they were afraid would never be induced to part with any of it to them, but for equivalent Returns of Glory and Profit to the Nation. They knew the Prince had a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k ſide, which might be better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ought upon: His towring Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt unlimited Deſires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Command and a noiſy Fame, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him continually to the bait they deſigned him; which was, to pay him in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Titles, empty Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and feigned Pretences of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quiouſneſs, for our good <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gold, and brave <hi>Engliſh</hi> Troops. The Plot hath ſucceeded, and we paid them very handſomly for the Trick they put upon us; we have made vaſt Iſſues of Men and Money; we have liberally fed thoſe needy Princes and their Troops; it is probable that more Money will be expected and demanded from us; what are we to have for all this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence we have already made, and yet can ſee no end of? What Cities, what Provinces, are we to have? Is the <hi>French</hi> Navy to be burnt, or put into our hands? Are our old Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the <hi>French</hi> Crown, at leaſt to the Maritime Provinces, to be made good unto us? Or are we to reap nothing but the vain Honour of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving contributed towards the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of our Neighbours, by our own Ruine?</p>
            <p>The Duties of Neighbourhood are mutual; and ſuppoſe them as ſtrong and binding as the Author of <hi>A Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a Friend concerning the French In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion</hi> would make them, they plead as ſtrongly for us as againſt us: There lies as great an Obligation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Confederates, to aſſiſt us in the Recovery of <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,</hi> as upon us to recover the loſt Provinces in <hi>Flanders</hi> and upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> for them: No doubt our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King hath taken Care for it in his Treaties with the Confederates; if he have not, it is a plain Diſcovery that the Intereſt of Foreigners is dearer to him than that of <hi>England.</hi> How unjuſt is it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ob us of the fruits of ſo many Millions ſpent, and of ſo many which are in hazard, with our Religion, Liberties, and our <hi>All</hi> to boot? If there be any effectual care taken for this, by his Treaties, it were very fit the Nation were made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it, and that we cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47544:21"/>
knew what we were to have, and what Security the Confederate Princes have given for making good ſuch Treaties; it muſt be more than Words and common Security, that can ballance the real Deeds and Kindneſſes which we are daily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring upon them.</p>
            <p>But I am afraid we have not ſo much as a bare Promiſe of any thing. The encreaſe and growing Strength of our Monarchy lies ſo viſibly croſs to the ſeveral Pretences and Intereſts of the Confederates, that they would be deaf to any ſuch Propoſal; and the Prince depends too much upon them for the ſupport of his preſent Title, to preſs ſuch ungrateful things. Can any Man of Reaſon believe that the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> will agree to have the <hi>French</hi> Fleet put into our hands, which would render us Sovereigns of the Ocean, as well as of the Narrow Seas? Or is it not next to Frenzie, to imagine that the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> will ever give way that we ſhould recover our antient Footing in <hi>France,</hi> either in whole, or in part; by which ſo many Catholick Cities and Provinces would be ſubjected to Hereticks, the Communication betwixt <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> cut off, by ſhutting up the Channel on both ſides; and our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy put into ſuch a condition as would viſibly ſhock the ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of that Houſe; which they would again reſume, upon recovery of their loſt Provinces? So that we are not to expect any new Acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with all this vaſt Expence, but are to reſt ſatisfied with the Honour, or Folly rather, of raiſing the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> to its antient Greatneſs; and building up a Power, which would more fatally threaten us and the reſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> than that which we muſt be at ſuch Pains and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to pull down.</p>
            <p>If the Proſpect of a ſucceſsful War be ſo little encouraging, what have we to fear and feel from an unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Iſſue? How ſadly may we come to be whipt, when we ſhall be obliged to take back our <hi>Abdicated</hi> Monarch, whether we will or no? There will be nothing then to truſt to for the Safety of our Religion and Liberties, but the good Nature and true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Temper of a Prince, whom in that Caſe we have injured, ſlighted, and deſpiſed to the laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: Nay, upon the Iſſue of a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful War againſt <hi>France,</hi> we may be obliged to undergo the ſame Fate. So far will this War, in any Event, be from terminating in an Eſtabliſhment of our preſent Settlement, that it doth viſibly tend to the contrary. This will appear no Paradox to any Man who doth exactly weigh the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Intereſts and Politicks of the ſeveral States of <hi>Europe,</hi> with Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to us, and amongſt themſelves. Such a curious and diligent Obſerver will quickly diſcover how much more agreeable King <hi>James</hi>'s Reſtauration would be to the ſecret concealed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of all our Neighbouring States, than the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s preſent Royalty.</p>
            <p>The good Intentions of <hi>France</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, is not to be doubted. The Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> after their Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47544:22"/>
upon <hi>France</hi> are ſatisfied, do cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly become Favourers of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reſtauration, both upon the account of Religion, and to remove a <hi>Dutch Stadtholder</hi> from being King of <hi>Britain;</hi> thereby to facilitate their antient Pretences upon thoſe revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Provinces. The <hi>Dutch</hi> will hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily agree to his Reſtauration, to get rid of their Stadtholder, who preſſeth ſo hard upon their Liberties; they will be in no more Fears from <hi>France,</hi> from this ſuppoſed Iſſue of the War; and the Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> would always oblige its Monarch to cover and protect them from the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> The beſt Wiſhes of <hi>Sweden</hi> cannot be wanting, were it only by the Admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi>'s Right, to place the Prince of <hi>Denmark</hi> a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move farther from the Crown; ſince his Acceſſion to the Royalty amongſt us, by Vertue of his Princeſs's Title, might endanger the Conqueſts which that Crown hath made upon <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi> And ſince the Politicks of <hi>Denmark,</hi> with relation to us, are ſolely levell'd at his Brother's Intereſt; whenever the Indignities done to the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> ſhall oblige them to reſume that Duty and Loyalty which is due from them to their kind old Father, who is ſtill rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to receive them, and to ſecure unto them thoſe Advantages which they can never expect from the Pr. of <hi>Orange;</hi> the Concurrence of that Crown towards King <hi>James</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration can be no longer wanting. I do but hint at things, which are of ſufficient Importance to make all true <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> who love their Country and their Liberties, to bethink them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſeriouſly how to cover and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure all thoſe great and valuable Rights from the Oppreſſion of the P. of <hi>Orange,</hi> the Miſeries, Poverties, and Dangers, which will inevitably at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend either a ſucceſsful or unſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful War. We have thrown our ſelves into a State-Hurricane, from which there is no way of eſcaping, but by reſtoring the juſt and legal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Nation into its antient and unqueſtioned Channel.</p>
            <p>Having fully eſtabliſhed and made out the firſt three Motives aſſigned for K. <hi>James</hi>'s Reſtauration, I ſhall enquire a little into the fourth and laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the Securing of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion for all future Ages. This appears a great Paradox to the Author of <hi>The Pretences to the</hi> French <hi>Invaſion examined;</hi> at which he falls into Exclamations againſt Mankind, as the oddeſt Piece of the Creation, for believing ſuch incredible things. But it is not his bold, impudent, and falſe Aſſertions, ſupported only by empty and noiſy Eloquence, which can hide the Danger from us, that our Religion as well as our Liberties and Properties lies under from this Revolution. For clearing the Truth and Weight of this Motive, I ſhall make it evident, That our Religion was in no probability of being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by K. <hi>James</hi>'s Practices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Revolution: That it was in our power to have ſecured it, even againſt our Fears and Jealouſies, without any Breach upon the antient Government; That the Dethroning
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47544:22"/>
of Monarchs upon the Pretence of <hi>Religion,</hi> hath been fatal and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to all the ſeveral Proteſtant States who attempted it; That ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all appearance, it will be equally fatal in our Caſe and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: And laſtly, I ſhall make it evident, from a full and diſtinct An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to all the Arguments adduced by the Authors againſt King <hi>James</hi>'s Reſtauration, that the beſt, ſureſt, and moſt infallible way, whereby to ſecure the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> upon laſting and durable Foundations, is, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to our Duty, and reſtoring our <hi>Abdicated Monarch</hi> by as general a Conſent as he was chaſed away by us.</p>
            <p>It is very natural and common with Mankind, and with Princes as well as others, to have ſome more particular regard towards thoſe of their own Religion, to wiſh them well, and to endeavour their eaſe, when it lies in their Power; ſo that it was nothing extraordinary to find King <hi>James</hi> labouring to give his Catholick Subjects a Right and Title to that eaſe and ſecurity, which the Laws of the Land had deprived 'em of. I do not believe that <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> in general, and the cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of People from Perſecution on that ſcore, can be rationally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as deſtructive and ruinous to the Proteſtant Religion; we ought to have a better Opinion of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our Faith, and be better convinced of their Truth and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, than to be afraid to have 'em baſſled or ſhaken, much leſs ruined, by the Reaſons of any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion. That Religion which dares not ſhew its Face publickly, and ſtand the ſhock of all its Adverſaries, without skeening it ſelf under the Severity of Penal Laws, furniſheth great Suſpicion to curious and pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men of its weakneſs and inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency: But this, I hope, is not our Caſe; our moſt holy Religion is built upon that Rock of Ages, which can never be ſhaken; is fortified by the Teſtimonies of the Law and the Prophets, and expreſsly contained in the Word of God, or derived from thence by clear and neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, and can ſubſiſt by its own worth and excellency, without rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the reſt of Mankind of that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty their Birth-right Intitles them to, and enſlaving Conſciences. So that King <hi>James</hi> his Principle about <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> if duly and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally Eſtabliſhed, will be allowed: But it is the Method we complained of, which diſcovered ſome farther Deſign than bare <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and thereby did viſibly threaten our Civil Rights and Liberties, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger our Religion.</p>
            <p>Why, truly the Meaſures taken were unjuſtifiable; but we know to whoſe Council and Advice they were owing: The whole was a Plot upon that Prince, to ſpoil the Project of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> which would have rivitted him in his Throne; and to improve his Inclinations for the Roman Religion to his own ruin and deſtruction. But ſuppoſe ſomething more was intended by ſome, than a bare <hi>Liberty;</hi> perhaps the opening,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47544:23"/>
a Door of Preferment to Catholicks, or the propagating that Religion over this Iſland: Such an undertaing is irrational, fooliſh and deſperate; can never be accompliſhed; and the impoſſibility of it is ſo plain and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, that no Man who underſtands the World, and knew <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men ſo well as King <hi>James</hi> did, could believe it practicable. And as to the miraculous and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Faith of Prieſts and new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, the zeal, folly, and warmneſs of their Brains, will always prevent any real Miſchiefs; nay, K. <hi>James</hi> his Reign, even upon the ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that it were as bad as is alledged, is an undeniable Proof that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, nor the Popiſh Religion Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in theſe Kingdoms, by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs or Authority of any Prince.</p>
            <p>I ſhall give it for granted, that all imaginable Methods were taken for propagating the Popiſh Religion; that they were indulged in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Exerciſes of it; that Court Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments were thrown upon them, meerly upon the account of their Religion, without any Vertue or M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit to Intitle them to it; that Proteſtants were abſolutely, and upon all occaſions, diſcourag'd, that it was endeavour'd to make the World <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ve, that all Favours and Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were for the one, and nothing but Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>races and Frowns for the other; that there was the greateſt Care, Pains and Application, in the World, made uſe of, to make the Army and Courts of Judicature. I do belive, by this ſuppoſition, I have out-done all that the moſt malicious Enemies will urge againſt K. <hi>James;</hi> and yet all the World knows what little Progreſs was made, how few Converts were gained, and how really weak their beſt and ſureſt Precautions did appear when it came to the touch. If ſo many of his Subjects, Soldiers and Servants, were prevailed upon by Fears and Jealouſies, which were maliciouſly and induſtriouſly heightened above what any reaſon, which was given for them, could well bear; what muſt then have been the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, if by real, publick, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Diſcoveries, the King's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to ruin the Eſtabliſhed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, had been made unqueſtionably plain and evident: Nothing leſs than an univerſal Defection, and his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Baniſhment from the Hearts and Affections of every Engliſh Man, could have followed.</p>
            <p>The Catholicks of <hi>Britain</hi> are not one of a hundred; they have neither Heads, Hearts, nor Hands enough to force a National Converſion. As the Proteſtants are the moſt Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, ſo the Laws and Conſtitutions are upon their ſide; their Civil Rights and Liberties are twiſted together with their Religious; and whoſoever ſtrikes at the laſt, muſt infallibly wound the firſt. It is not eaſie to overturn the Laws and Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Conſtitutions, whereby Religious and Civil Rights are ſecured to free born People; we are in Poſſeſſion by our Laws of our Religion, and of that Liberty which diſtinguiſheth our Happineſs from that of other
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47544:23"/>
Subjects; we love it, and know it's true worth; we value and eſteem our ſelves above other People, upon the account of our native Freedoms, and we will not eaſily part with 'em; all Attempts and Deſigns upon them have been unſucceſsful. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Princes, and Arbitrary Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters may be forming Projects and Deſigns, fortifying them the beſt way they can, and making Parties for it; but our Conſtitution, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Proteſtant Religion, which is now become part of it, and our Laws, will prove always too hard for them at laſt: Nothing can expoſe or betray our Religion and Conſtitution to any danger, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch fondneſs in the People to a Prince, who under ſome popular Mask and Pretence, covers cloſe and fatal Deſigns againſt either. Let us but examine the preſent condition of our neighbouring States, and we ſhall find that Raptures of Love in the people hath overturned more Conſtitutions, and built up more De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotick Governments, than the Force or Addreſs of Princes could ever do. It is commonly received for a Truth, That <hi>Love is blind</hi> and credulous, and certainly holds good, with relation to a Political Affection. There is a certain allowable Jealouſie in the People, which is very conſiſtent with the Duty, Affection, and Reſpect due to the Prince; and guards and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects their Laws and Conſtitution. Without ſome Meaſures of this Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, the Conſtitution will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in danger; and this Antidote can never be wanting in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Subjects of <hi>Britain,</hi> under a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh King: His Religion gives us ſuch a lively and active Jealouſie of him, and his Deſigns makes us ſo watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and puts us ſo much upon our guard, that all the Efforts of ſuch a Prince, thô never ſo dextrous, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by ſo weak and inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Party as the Catholicks of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> can never endanger Religion and Liberty. Rather his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Inclinations to thoſe of his own Religion, their eaſe and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, might have been improved into farther and more real Securities for Religion and Liberty, by a wiſe and diſcreet Treaty, orderly managed in Parliament.</p>
            <p>To all this it may be alledged, That though the Catholicks of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> be not a Party ſufficient to carry on, and effectuate ſuch Deſigns; yet the Forces of the <hi>Hector</hi> of <hi>France</hi> were ſtill at the Command and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Dear and Faithful Ally, for carrying on ſo good and merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a Work, as that of Reducing again <hi>Great Britan</hi> into the Boſom of the <hi>Roman Church:</hi> This is mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly and artfully enough ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but let us examin it a little. How does it appear that King <hi>James</hi> was become ſo loſt to all Reaſon, Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Diſcretion, as to reſolve to call in a <hi>French Power</hi> to over-run a Countrey which was his own, and deſtroy a People who were living peaceably under him; by which, from one of the moſt Conſiderable and Potent Monarchs of <hi>Europe,</hi> he became the Leaſt and moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible? His refuſal of French
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47544:24"/>
Troops and Aſſiſtance, when threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened with a Foreign Invaſion, ſeems to be no great Proof of this; and his betaking himſelf at that time to the Love and Affection of his Subjects, as it was a plain diſcovery he was not Conſcious to himſelf of any real Deſign, which could deſtroy that mutual Love and Confidence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Prince and People, which is a Debt due from the one to the other, however his Meaſures might have been Traduced, or maliciouſly Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned; ſo it may let us ſee how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable it is to imagine, that a Prince could ever form Deſigns of deſtroying a People whoſe Affections he durſt truſt in ſuch an Extremity. Again, What Reaſon is there to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that the French King vvould be ſo ready to furniſh Troops, and be at the Charge of ſuch a Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? He is generally allowed to be a Prince who ſtudies his own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the moſt of any; and fits all his Maxims, his Conduct and Allyances, exactly to it; and never takes a ſtep, which upon the remoteſt view, may ſeem to croſs the Intereſt of his Crown and Monarchy: And if it do appear, as certainly it will to any judicious thinking Man, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing <hi>Great Britain</hi> to the Boſom of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> may greatly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> than all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rs of a <hi>French Reformation</hi> will fall to the Ground.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh Pretences to the moſt conſiderable Maritime Provinces, nay upon the Crown of <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, are generally known; and Hiſtories can inform us how troubleſome, how dangerous, and how ſucceſsfully they were many times carried on againſt thoſe Monarchs; partly by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Boldneſs, Spirit, and Courage of the Engliſh, far ſurpaſſing that of the French; but more eſpecially from the Inclination of the French themſelves to live under a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which was ſo much eaſier, and more agreeable than their own; it being natural for People to covet the ſame Plenty and Freedom, which they ſee is injoyed and poſſeſſed by their Neighbour. Hence it was, that though we loſt all our Footing in <hi>France,</hi> yet ſtill our Forces and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity was more dreadful to thoſe Monarchs, than that of any other State in <hi>Europe,</hi> though more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable for its native Strength, and conſining by dry Marches upon 'em; and they always Courted our Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Allyance, with the greateſt Submiſſions and Applications imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: And until the Reign of Q. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> the French did always chuſe rather to divert our Invaſions with their Money and Treaties, than to encounter them by Force; being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to graple with that Power, which they had ſo often felt to their Coſt. Since that time, neither our Friendſhip hath been ſo much Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor our Enmity ſo carefully Avoided as formerly. This doth not proceed from the increaſe of the French Power, and decreaſe of ours; though the Revenues and Military Force of <hi>France</hi> be ſtrangely aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented ſince; ours, in proportion, hath received the ſame increaſe: Our Treaſure is augmented; and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:47544:24"/>
that being the Sinews of War, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furniſheth and maintains every thing elſe: And the other States of <hi>Europe</hi> are, from the Circumſtances of Affairs, better diſpoſed for Ally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances with us, than ever they were in the time of our Anceſtors. So that <hi>France</hi> is but ſtill <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> in the ſame Proportion with it, as to Force and Revenue; and in a more promiſing Condition of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Allyances, and of being more uſefully ſerved by them: Our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences are ſtill the ſame, and every whit as Strong and Juſt, and we as willing and deſirous to make Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of them; and yet we are in no reſpect ſo formidable to that Crown, as formerly; nor in a Condition to ſhake that State, and make ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions into the Heart of <hi>France,</hi> as our Anceſtors have done: The true Reaſon is our difference in Religon; for we being Proteſtants, and <hi>France</hi> Popiſh; this ſets the Two Nations at a greater diſtance from mutual Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence and Contrivances, which muſt neceſſarily preceed and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion important Revolutions, than all their former Animoſities, Emulation, and Duty to their natural Prince could ever do. Loyalty to Princes, National Conſiderations, and Point of Honor and Reputation, do many times give way to preſent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Advantages: But when Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Point of Conſcience comes in to gather and cement all thoſe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Intereſts together, and unite them, as it were, into one bundle, they become the more hard and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to overcome. This plain and evident Reaſon cannot eſcape the Knowledge and Reflection of ſo wiſe a Prince, as the French King is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be. The difference in Religion is a much greater Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to him againſt our Attempts, than his Armies, Fleets, or Strength of his Towns. The Senſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doth many times rouze and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the Courage and Reſolutions of Men, when other humane Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations prove to weak to quicken their drooping Spirits: <hi>Catholicks</hi> will fight to the laſt, to eſcape the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of ſuch as they believe <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks;</hi> when, perhaps, French Men would be willing enough to come under the Engliſh Government, which is ſo much eaſier and better than their own. I do not queſtion but this very Conſideration alone, will prove ſtrong enough to keep the French King from endeavouring our Reunion to the <hi>Roman Church;</hi> which would make the Pretences of an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Monarch more dangerous, than ever by our Union with <hi>Scotland,</hi> which formerly gave ſuch notable Diverſions to our Forces both at Home and in <hi>France:</hi> That <hi>Prince</hi>'s Diſputes with the <hi>Pope,</hi> for Point of Prerogative, ſhews plainly that he never will indanger his Crown in his own Perſon, or Poſterity, to ſerve the Intereſts and Deſires of the <hi>Papal Chair;</hi> from all which we may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude, that the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in <hi>Britain,</hi> was in no great danger of being ruined by King <hi>James,</hi> though really as bad as he was repreſented.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:47544:25"/>If our Religion and Liberties were placed ſo much out of danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overturned, by the Laws and Franchiſes we were then in Poſſeſſion of, how much better might we have eſtabliſhed them for the future, and placed them above the ſhadow of any Danger, by embracing and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Offers which our lawful Prince made us, of carving out our own Satisfaction and Securities. He was ſurprized with an aſtoniſhing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his Subjects, with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of a great many Princes and States againſt him. He knew no place but <hi>France</hi> to retire unto; where he might have a Cover for his Head, but could have no great Expectations of being quickly reſtored to his Throne by a Power which had ſo much other Diverſion. He was unwilling in his old Age to go into Exile, was very deſirous to leave a perfect Calm to his Son, before his own Death, which by the Co rſ of Nature, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Deſtiny of his Family, he could not believe was very remote; and had a Love and Kindneſs to us ſtill, as a Father for his diſobedient Children. All which would have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured us, from our lawful King, a laſting, legal, full, and happy Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement; would have eſtabliſhed our Religion, bettered and ſecured our Liberties upon laſting Foundations, without any trouble, and with a great deal of innocency. How many crimes would have been avoided by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Method; and how many more prevented, which will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, if we be obſtinate, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and maintain the Injuſtice we have done? How many Millions of Money, and how many Lives might have been ſaved, or at leaſt more profitably employed, by the Conduct and good Husbandry of our Lawful King, for the Honour of <hi>England,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining the unbounded Pretences of ambitious Neighbours, and in giving Peace and Quiet to <hi>Europe?</hi> There is no queſtion, but a King who was ſo unwilling to leave us, and had ſo much of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Spirit, would have gone into any Meaſures, with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to foreign Affairs, that his Palia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould have thought fitting; in which caſe, what returns of Glory and Profit would this Nation and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy have reaped from this Blood and Treaſure, which is now abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſt and thrown away, and our future Expences and Dangers daily growing upon us, with as little hope of Succeſs? My heart is ſo rent and torn with the thoughts of it, that my Pen is ready to drop out of my hand as I write: But we wantonly longed for an <hi>Abdication,</hi> without examining the true Value of what we refuſed, and the Conſequences were to follow upon the other Meaſures. We have made a religious War of it, which may be fatally returned upon us; and we never conſidered that Defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon Pretences for the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, ſeldom or never ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate othervviſe than by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Pretenders</hi> both. It ſeems God Almighty did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways diſcover more of Paſſion and Worldly Deſigns, than true Zeal for Religion, in thoſe Undertakings; and I am afraid, That ſince we deſerve
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:47544:25"/>
the like Charge, our Puniſhment may be the ſame, unleſs by a ſeaſonable and early Repentance we prevent it.</p>
            <p>The firſt Example I find in Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is <hi>Ziſca</hi>'s War in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> againſt the Emperor <hi>Sigiſmond;</hi> which thô managed as ſucceſsfully in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as any thing we can flatter our ſelves with, yet had an end very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to the Reformation in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. The Civil Wars in <hi>Germany,</hi> managed by the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> and the Landgrave of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> againſt <hi>Charles</hi> V. had no better Iſſue; many Imperial Cities and Provinces were lopt off from our Communion, and the principal Actors themſelves were remarkably Sufferers by it, and their Families wear the Scars of it to this day. The ſecond <hi>Bohemian</hi> War, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> whom they had choſen for their King, was yet more fatal to that Kingdom than the firſt, and almoſt ruined the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> did exceedingly weaken the Proteſtant Intereſt in <hi>Germany,</hi> and laid the Foundation for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Grandure of <hi>France,</hi> which is ſo terrible to <hi>Europe</hi> at this time: Upon the Event of that War the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Rights and Liberties of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as well as the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the Kingdom of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> were intirely ruined and extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: The principal Electorate of the Empire, together with the Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> were wreſted out of a Proteſtant, and placed in a Popiſh Family: Several other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Princes and States were loſt; and the French poſſeſſed of both the <hi>Alſatias,</hi> which hath ſince given in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Diſturbances to that Empire. And the <hi>Hungarian</hi> War commenced firſt upon pretence of Religion, and came at laſt to be managed by <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely,</hi> hath quite buried the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion in <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania;</hi> and it is very Remarkable, That ſo long as they kept Petitioning as Subjects, <hi>(Though with Arms in their Hands, for the free Exerciſe of their Religion,)</hi> they were conſtantly Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious, and got into the abſolute Poſſeſſion of the greateſt part of that Kingdom; and might have fully ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured their Religion and Liberties, by Conceſſions and Immunities which the Emperor offered them in repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Treaties: And yet no ſooner was the Crown given to <hi>Tekely,</hi> and an Allyance made with the Turks to ſupport him in it, but by a ſeries of Misfortunes all their former Succeſſes were unravelled, and their Affairs reduced to the miſerable Condition we now ſee them in.</p>
            <p>What ſad alarms may ſuch Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces give us? How truly do they point at our Caſe; and perhaps our Fate? Can any of the above-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Examples diſcover ſuch plain and viſible Marks of worldly Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Self-intereſt, and corrupted Deſigns and Artifices, for their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, as have evidently actuated the Contrivers of and principal Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in our <hi>Revolution?</hi> And yet how fatally were they puniſhed? And can we hope to eſcape? The Emperor <hi>Ferdinando</hi> was in a worſe Condition to reſiſt the Elector <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> backed by the Proteſtant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Germany,</hi> countenanced by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:47544:26"/>
               <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> and the preſent Emperour <hi>Rodolph</hi> was under har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Circumſtances to ſupport a War againſt his <hi>Hungarian Rebels,</hi> and the <hi>Turkiſh Power,</hi> than any that <hi>France</hi> hath to graple with from <hi>Us</hi> and our <hi>Allies;</hi> and yet their numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and ſtrong Allies, could not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them from thoſe Miſeries which did at laſt overtake them. There is no way for us to get ſafe from the Precepices we have been walking upon, to retrieve our Religion from the deſperate Danger we have run it into, and to ſetle and ſecure it; but by a National returning to our Duty, which will ſufficiently atone for ſo general a Defection, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming that Treaty we ſo fooliſhly br k off and refuſed; and thereby ſecuring Religion and Property, by thoſe Conceſſions which our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign is ſtill ready to grant us: Let us put it home to him, and lay it at his own Door; let him have it in his Choice to return by his People if he pleaſeth; convince him that his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Subjects, upon ſecuring their Religion and Liberties, will repair their former Errors, by contributing heartily towards his Reſtauration. And if he decline to return upon a Proteſtant and Engliſh Foot, there is an end of the Controverſie, and of all Diſputes amongſt Proteſtants; for Religion and Liberty will never be Sacrificed by true Engliſh Men.</p>
            <p>I am come in the laſt place to the Objections raiſed, by the new Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, againſt King <hi>James</hi>'s return; which are ſtuffed with virulent, falſe, and ſophiſtical Reaſonings; and, in a great Meaſure, taken off by what hath been already ſaid. The firſt thing they endeavour to frighten us with, is a <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> and with <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> as the neceſſary Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it; ſince it is impoſſible K. <hi>James</hi> can return otherways, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe K. <hi>William</hi> will not <hi>Abdicate.</hi> I abhor the thoughts of <hi>Conquering</hi> my native Countrey, as much as any Man; more it ſeems than <hi>The Author of a Letter to a Friend,</hi> who would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of it in the Perſon of K. <hi>William,</hi> and I am againſt it in any Caſe. But by whom are we to be <hi>Conquered;</hi> and to whom muſt the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long? Are we to be <hi>Conquered</hi> by ſuch Troops as K. <hi>James,</hi> in point of Prudence, and according to the practiſes of all Ages in the like Caſe, muſt bring with him for the defence of his Perſon, and the untying of that Force which the Prince hath put upon us? I know no reaſon, why it may not be as Lawful for K. <hi>James</hi> to bring Fifteen thouſand Men to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him in recovering his Throne, as it was for the P. of O. to bring the like Number to chaſe him out of it; and that without giving any Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to us of a Conqueſt? Thrice that Number were too few to make a Conqueſt of this Iſland; and I hope they will be ſo well ſeconded, and ſo far out numbered by the Acceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own Subjects, upon a feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcovery of the Pr. of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Tyranny, as well as of the Injuſtice done their King; as may juſtly Stamp it a Revolution brought about by Engliſh Men, who have Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Paſſions and not their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:47544:26"/>
reſcued, and not enſlaved the Nation; and who have preſerved, and not endangered their Religion.</p>
            <p>Is this imaginary Conqueſt to make us Slaves to the Fr. King, or Catholicks and Slaves to K. <hi>James?</hi> I cannot believe the firſt: For I do not think K. <hi>James</hi> ſo much in love with the French King, as to make him a Preſent of Three Crowns to the prejudice of Himſelf and his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; and ſo become either his Subject, or his Vaſſal. Theſe are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions fit only to paſs upon Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, deſerves no ſerious Anſwer; and plainly ſhews the weakneſs of the Cauſe, which can furniſh no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Reaſons wherewith to defend it. As to the laſt; The French King will never force us to be Catholicks, for the Reaſons already aſſigned; and it doth as little agree with his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, to have us Slaves to our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. Friendſhips are ſeldom laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongſt Neighbouring Princes, rarely continue during their own Lives, and are never tranſmitted to to their Poſterities; ſo many Reaſons and Jealouſies of State are falling in, which occaſion frequent and unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Breaches: And a King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> who is Abſolute and Maſter of his Subjects, would be a great deal more troubleſome and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to <hi>France</hi> than otherways; and ſo it is not very probable that that Monarch will ever contribute to make us a Conqueſt to K. <hi>James,</hi> and introduce Popery and Slavery amongſt us. There is one ſure way to prevent this danger of Conqueſt, and that is by the vigorous endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of every Enliſh Man, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the Injury done to our <hi>Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Monarch.</hi> King <hi>William</hi>'s unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to <hi>Abdicate,</hi> which theſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors threaten us with, can't put a ſtop to it: His breaches upon our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and his viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Original Contract</hi> made with himſelf deſerves it; and it is not all his <hi>Partiſans</hi> and <hi>Troops,</hi> can cover him from <hi>Abdication</hi> whenever the People of <hi>England</hi> thinks fit to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it.</p>
            <p>We are told next by theſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, <hi>That K.</hi> James <hi>is become ſo in love with the French Government, that we ſhall never ſo much as have his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for ſecuring our Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, even though we have no reaſon to depend upon that, or any other Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity he can give us; ſince he hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to the Pope and K. of</hi> France <hi>to make void all when he is upon his Throne; and that it is viſible from his Carriage in</hi> Ireland <hi>to the Proteſtants there, that neither the ſad Example of K.</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt, who ſuffered for the like Attempts towards Arbitrary Power, nor the freſh Remembrances of his own Misfortunes, will ever oblige him to lay aſide his Arbitrary Deſigns: And however inſtrumental Proteſtants may be in his return, that Pardon for their former Failings is all can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from him, without obtaining the leaſt kind regard to their Religion or Liberties on that Score.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would gladly know upon what Grounds they aſſert, that K. <hi>James</hi> will grant no Security at all for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Liberty? Have they made the Experiment, and been
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:47544:27"/>
refuſed? It is not a bare Aſſertion can convince us of the Truth of it, ſince we are aſſured to the contrary. I have heard of a Scotch Plot for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring King <hi>James;</hi> the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of it I am not acquainted with: Only I have been told, <hi>That upon the Application of ſome few Gentlemen of that Nation unto him, he frankly gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, under the Broad Seal of</hi> Scotland, <hi>all that was propoſed for the ſecurity of Religion and Liberty; and agreed to ſeveral Immunities which the P. of O. refuſed that Nation, though he was ſolemnly engaged to grant them when the Crown of that Kingdom was tendered unto him.</hi> Here is more than a bare Promiſe; the Conceſſions are paſſed under the Broad Seal, and granted by him, when his Affairs were in Promiſing Circumſtances, at the deſire of a few Gentlemen who had been active againſt him, and who could make no ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Addition unto his Party, as might induce him to it; unleſs his own Inclinations, when free from the preſſure of deſigning Miniſters, and readineſs to rectifie whatever was grievous to the People, had put him upon it. Can it be doubted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, that he will deny any thing that is neceſſary for the good and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of his Subjects whenever they apply ſeriouſly unto him for it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But he muſt make good his Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the Pope and King of</hi> France, <hi>and make void all when he remounts the Throne, which his hard Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances obliged him to grant.</hi> If this were made plain unto us, there would be a great deal of weight in it; all the Evidence we have for it is the Veracity of the Author, which goeth no great length; being foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only upon ſuppoſition, that he could not be countenanced by thoſe Princes without ſuch an Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This is an Argument that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes more forcibly againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; ſince it is reaſonable to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that more ſolemn and ſacred Engagements in favour of the <hi>Holy Chair,</hi> and a Conviction of more punctual and ready Performances, were neceſſary to induce the Pope, and ſo many Popiſh Princes to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance a Proteſtants mounting the Throne, to the prejudice of a Papiſt.</p>
            <p>I am yet to learn what were the great Merits of the Iriſh Proteſtants ſince the Revolution, the freſh Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations laid upon him, and what were the new Diſcoveries he gave us there of his hatred to Proteſtants, and irregular Arbitrary Courſes. I have ſeen a Book written by Dr. <hi>King,</hi> which theſe Authors refers us to, as ſufficient Evidence to make good their Charge; but it is ſo ſcandalouſly and notoriouſly Falſe, and ſtuffed with ſo many groſs Errors, and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miſtakes, in point of Hiſtory and matter of Fact, even in many things which fall under my own Knowlege, that the Doctor ſeems to have Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated his Book for a Virulent falſe Libel; thereby to merit ſome Beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from this Government, rather than for our Information by a true and impartial Hiſtory: And the World ſhall be obliged with a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Account of his Falſhoods and Calumnies, by a full and impartial
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:47544:27"/>
Account of thoſe Tranſactions. But to come cloſe home to the Charge; Did not the Iriſh Proteſtants general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare for the Prince of <hi>Orange?</hi> Did they not actually either appear in Arms for the Prince, or quit the Kingdom? And thoſe who ſtay'd, were not they rather lookers on than actors, or any ways uſeful towards the aſſerting the King's Rights? I do not deſign this as a <hi>Satyr</hi> againſt the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland;</hi> the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures taken there gave them much better grounds for their Fears than any we can pretend; but only to ſhew that the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> contributed no Endeavours towards his Reſtauration, but run generally along with the Stream againſt it; and ſo cannot be ſaid to have made any new Experiment of his Kindneſs to, and grateful ſenſe of Obligations performed by Proteſtants. They ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſired, or obtained, any new Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities for their Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, upon the Account of Services performed for him; and ſo have no freſh Branches of Promiſe to charge upon him, as our Authors do inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, whereby to deter the Proteſtants of <hi>Britain</hi> from contributing towards his Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, we have a very convincing Argument, from his Care of his Proteſtant Subjects there, tho' either actually Enemies, or at beſt but idle Spectators; and his conſtant Endeavours to protect them from the Inſults and Fury of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> of whom he was not fully Maſter; to perſuade us of the Gratitude and kind Returns we may exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct from him, when at liberty, and obliged by our Services, to expreſs it. How carefully did he preſerve their Eſtates and Goods? With how much tenderneſs did he give free Paſſage to the Women and Children from <hi>Londonderry,</hi> when by denying it he muſt infallibly have carried the Town? With what exact Diſcipline did he Govern an Army, ſerving without Pay, until King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi>'s Proteſtant reforming Troops which were under Pay, by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Plunderings, Robberies, and Oppreſſions, committed upon the poor Proteſtants within their Lines, gave ſuch Examples of Inſolence and looſe Diſcipline, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> could be no longer reſtrained, as formerly, thô they never acted ſo extravagant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the others. And I dare appeal to all the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants, if the greateſt part of the ruine of that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Country be not due to the Plunderings, Abuſes, and want of Diſcipline, in King <hi>William</hi>'s Army; which, though Proteſtant, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, did far outdoe the wild <hi>Iriſh</hi> in deſolating the Country, without regard to Friend or Foe: And I have heard many <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants affirm, That their Preſervation and Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was due to K. <hi>James</hi>'s own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Care over them.</p>
            <p>As to the Proceedings of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Parliament, he did ſo much wreſtle againſt them, was ſo little Maſter of himſelf and Actions, and ſo much in the hands of <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that he is rather to be pitied than blamed for them: And 'tis very hard and unreaſonable, that when a King is forced from a Throne by his Proteſtant Subjects, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:47544:28"/>
by them in his Endeavours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the recovery of his Inheritance, and ſo neceſſitated to betake himſelf to the Aſſiſtance, Protection, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of Catholicks, unleſs he would Renounce his undoubted Rights, which neither the Laws of God nor Man oblige him to; that Acts of Grace, which his Circumſtances, and the neceſſity of their Aſſiſtance, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from him, ſhould be charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him as Crimes. Let us labour for his Reſtauration; let us get him into our hands, and deliver him from that cruel Neceſſity which carries him far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than his Inclinations would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe do; and whenever he is at liberty to act as an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> he will convince us that he is ſuch.</p>
            <p>The Treatment that <hi>Charles</hi> I. met with is a ſad Inſtance of the Vanity of all human Greatneſs, and a laſting Reproach to our Nation; but reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a more pertinent and appoſite Reproof to K. <hi>William</hi>'s Conduct, than K. <hi>James</hi>'s. The moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and important points which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned thoſe fatal Diſputes betwixt that Prince and his People, were ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Impriſonments, the undue refuſal of Liberty to Priſoners upon Bail, the free quarterings and Plunderings of Soldiers, and the unwarrantable exacting of Money from the Subject without Conſent of Parliament. Are not all theſe illegal and arbitrary pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices frequently repeated in this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and without any Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from K. <hi>James</hi>'s Reign?</p>
            <p>The many Pages imploy'd by the Author of <hi>A Letter to a Friend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the French Invaſion,</hi> to prove, <hi>That the Non-ſwearing Proteſtants, as well as others, can merit nothing by their endeavours for the King's Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but a bare Pardon at moſt,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers more Logick and Method in dividing of his Text, than true, ſolid and convincing Reaſon: For ſince a few Scotiſh Gentlemen, who had acted warmly and vigorouſly againſt him, and could contribute but little to his Service, were able to procure not only Pardon, but thoſe great and important Securities for their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the Liberties of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which K. <hi>William</hi> had refuſed to the Deſires and Addreſſes of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament that had given him the Crown, and pre engaged his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent before the Gift: Is it to be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, That ſo many worthy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Lords, Gentlemen, and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Clergy, who have teſtified ſo much Zeal, Firmneſs, and Fidelity, by their Sufferings, joyn'd with the early Repentance and vigorous Endeavors of others for his Service, who have been hitherto blinded and miſled, will not prove of more Weight, Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Conſideration, with him; be as kindly treated, and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for their ſakes: Or rather, will not all Securities for Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty be granted, from a due regard to their Application, as well as from his own Inclination? Neither is it to be feared that any of their former Meaſures, which unhappily and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally have contributed towards that Ferment which begot this Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, will be remembred againſt them; ſince the King is ſenſible how far he himſelf was impoſed upon, as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47544:28"/>
well as his Subjects, by the Cunning and Artifice of wicked and corrupted Miniſters which were about him. And whatever Jealouſies this Author may labour to infuſe into the minds of People, of the firey and lax Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> with Relation to the Proteſtant Religion, Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Engliſh Liberties; there are <hi>Jacobites,</hi> whoſe Principles are better, more fixed and rational, who have already, and will upon all occaſions never fail to give greater and more generous Teſtimonies of their zeal and affection for the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment and Security of thoſe great Concerns, than any can be brought by our preſent Miniſters and topping Reformers; and who will never be found with this Author in juſtifying a Conqueſt of their native Country.</p>
            <p>The Caution which is given us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another Revolution, leſt the Monarchy receive more vigour from a Reſtauration, than is convenient for the Liberties of the Subject, which the Author fortifies from an Inſtance in the Return of <hi>Charles</hi> II. at which time, betwixt zeal, flattery, and fear, the King encreaſed in Power, and the People loſt their Liberties; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes very ſtrongly againſt himſelf, and for what I have been all along preſſing. If we do but conſider the true reaſon of thoſe Conceſſions made in favour of the Monarchy, upon the Return of K. <hi>Charles,</hi> the Nation was ſo wearied out, exhauſted and undone, by the Tyrannies and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, Taxes, Impriſonments, and other arbitrary Courſes againſt their Liberties and Properties, that were practiced during that Anarchy which intervened betwixt the Murther of the Father and Return of the Son, that upon a Proſpect of ſome Relief, by the reeſtabliſhment of the antient Monarchy, the People fell into ſuch Raptures of Joy, which never fails of making Subjects ſo liberal to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as many times occaſions a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty but late Repentance. If K. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> continue a little longer to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs our Liberties, and drein our Purſes; or if the Title of <hi>Conqueſt</hi> be advanced, we ſhall be infallibly expoſed to the like hazard again; which cannot be prevented, but by an early Return to our Duty, whilſt we have ſome Patience, Wit and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, left, to enable us to take care of our ſelves and our Poſterity.</p>
            <p>The hard and difficult Queſtions which this Author thinks he hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled us with, and the obligation of the Oaths of Allegiance to K. <hi>William,</hi> comes next to be conſidered. The firſt Queſtion is, Whether we think our ſelves bound in Conſcience to fight for Popery againſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Faith. I Anſwer not; nor doth this Anſwer make any thing for King <hi>William,</hi> ſince in no Senſe can the fighting for the Reſtauration of King <hi>James</hi> be called the fighting for Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery againſt the Proteſtant Religion; for it is both K. <hi>James</hi>'s Intereſt and his Inclination to return upon a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Foot; and by aſſiſting him in it, we vindicate the Honor of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and reſcue it from the Dangers which threatens it from this Reign.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Queſtion is, Whether we think our ſelves bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:47544:29"/>
to fight for our Prince againſt the Laws and Liberties of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. I Anſwer in the Negative; and we do aſſure the World, That it is from a tender regard to our Laws and Liberties, as well as from a ſenſe of Duty, to repair the injury done our Exiled Prince, that we reſolve to contribute to his return. The antient Conſtitution was broke in upon by the <hi>Abdication,</hi> and our Laws, Rights and Liberties, have been more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently and ſignally over-run during the P. of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Kingſhip, than by any of our moſt Violent and Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Princes, even when he was under the greateſt Obligation, cleareſt and diſtinct Barriers placed againſt it; and we are poſſeſſed with reaſonable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ars, nay a certainty of having 'em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ruined and extinguiſhed by his future Conduct, which layeth an Obligation upon all true Engliſh Men to repair theſe Breaches made upon the Conſtitution, and to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and reſtore their oppreſſed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ined Laws and Liberties, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning K. <hi>James</hi> and the P. of <hi>O.</hi> into their proper and reſpective Stations.</p>
            <p>But we are deſired and preſſed to have ſome Care of the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Church of Chriſt, which will be viſibly endang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red by the King's Reſtauration all <hi>Europe</hi> over; and a due regard for the Rights and Liberties of all the Princes in <hi>Europe,</hi> which will be ſacrificed by it; that this ought to be more tenderly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by us, ſince we are Citizens of the World; and ſo the good of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, or the greateſt part of it, layeth a more ſacred Obligation upon us, and is to be preferred to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſt of our own Prince and Countrey. The ſecurity of Religion is a Duty never to be forgotten by good Proteſtants, and is never to be endangered and deſperately hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by honeſt Men. But, alas! this hath been little regarded by our <hi>late Reformers.</hi> Have they not quite un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinged our Conſtitution, of which the Proteſtant Religion was become a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part? Have they not already, and are they not in a fair way to ruine our Laws and Liberties, which are the beſt Fences about our Religion? After we are become <hi>Slaves,</hi> we may quickly be made any thing elſe; the multitude of new Converts in <hi>France,</hi> is an undeniable Inſtance of this. Have they not unneceſſarily expoſed the Proteſtant Religion, to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of a rude and uncertain War; from the commencement of which, we can form no great hopes of a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Iſſue, and that in Conjunction with Allies, who are the greateſt Enemies of our Religion; who when their particular Intereſts have been ſerved by our Blood and Treaſure, will certainly give us the ſlip, and nick ſome Opportunity, which our preſent Circumſtances can never fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with, of Eſtabliſhing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the Expence of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Civil Rights and Liberties? And finally, have we not dethroned our King, upon the account of his Religion; by which we have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced a religious War, which may come to be fatally retorted upon us, and may endanger the whole Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:47544:29"/>A religious War is carefully to be avoided by Proteſtants, ſince they are the weakeſt; and no Pretence ought to be furniſhed to the Catholicks for the like Meaſure: For thô particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Animoſities and Intereſt ſeem to divide them at preſent, how quickly may theſe be adjuſted by the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of one of the contending Parties, and how eaſie will it be then for the Pope to unite them together under the Banners of Religion, to give us, and the Proteſtants of <hi>Europe,</hi> a <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for our <hi>Oliver?</hi> This is no <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera</hi> or Dream; but we may proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly expect to ſee and feel it. A far weaker Pretence, <hi>viz.</hi> the Union e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed amongſt the Proteſtants of <hi>Germany,</hi> at <hi>Leipſick</hi> and <hi>Smalcald,</hi> gave Birth to the Catholick League there; which over-run all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, forced ſeveral Princes and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from their Communion, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered <hi>Denmark.</hi> It is upon ſuch weighty Conſiderations, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the danger which threatens the Proteſtant Religion both at home and abroad, from our late Meaſures, that all true <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> and good Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ought to endeavour the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of our King.</p>
            <p>As to the Caution given us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how we ſacrifice the Rights and Liberties of all the Princes in <hi>Europe;</hi> the greateſt part of the Princes and States of <hi>Europe</hi> are not engaged in this War againſt <hi>France,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in no danger by it: The two Northern Crowns, <hi>Moſcovy</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Portugal,</hi> all the Princes and States of <hi>Italy,</hi> except <hi>Savoy,</hi> together with the <hi>Switzers,</hi> are in perfect Peace with <hi>France;</hi> and ſo the Suppoſition of this Author is abſolutely falſe; the Original and Ground of this War is purely private Conteſts betwixt the Crown of <hi>France</hi> and Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> and ſuch other Princes as that Houſe can draw into their Intereſt. Do we not ſee that the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> themſelves, who ſeem to have the moſt immediate Concern in it, and ſhould underſtand and be more alarmed at the Conſequences of it than we, do but make Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of their Aſſiſtance, and engage in and withdraw from this War, as it contributes moſt to their particular Intereſts, and according as they are beſt paid by the ſeveral Principals? Do not the Northern Crowns, whoſe Territories and Provinces lie more expoſed to the Conſequences of this War than our Iſlands, maintain an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Neutrality, which will give their Subjects Poſſeſſion of the beſt part of the Trade of <hi>Europe?</hi> We are the only Fools who have been prevailed upon to engage inconſiderately in this War, to be at the greateſt Charge of it, to drein our Blood and Treaſure, and to hazard our Religion and Liberties by it, without ſo much as propoſing any Return to ballance this Expence and Danger. Our Conduct is ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Folly and Madneſs, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazeth the preſent, and will not find Credit in future Ages.</p>
            <p>As to the Maxim eſtabliſhed by the Author, upon which he buildeth all his fine Reaſoning, it is falſe and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natical to perfection. Can any Man in his right Wits aſſert That the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of our Prince and Country muſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:47544:30"/>
give place to the Intereſts of other States, ſuppoſe them to be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of Mankind? Much leſs then to thoſe of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which is the preſent Caſe. Muſt the Intereſt of the Britiſh Monarchy be poſtponed to the Intereſt of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometan and Pagan Countries, which make the greateſt part of Mankind: Or muſt the Intereſt of <hi>Britain,</hi> and ſo of the Proteſtant Religion, which makes a part of it, give way to the Intereſt of the Pope and Catholick Princes, which make the greateſt part of <hi>Europe?</hi> We may quickly gueſs what our Fate would be by following ſuch a Rule, and may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be perſuaded that the Cauſe muſt be very bad, which requires ſuch wretched Maxims and Reaſonings to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pport it.</p>
            <p>The laſt Queſtion is, Whether we would think our ſelves bound to ſight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, did we believe he would promote the ſame Deſigns he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and what we would think our ſelves obliged to do in the like caſe, and under the ſame Circumſtances, after he had remounted the Throne. The Anſwer is plain and obvious: By this Revolution, and the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and ſhare in theſe Meaſures with which K. <hi>James</hi> was loaded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufficiently diſcovered to the World; together with the Roguery of thoſe Miniſters, who to ſerve the Prince's Deſign forced the King un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly enough upon thoſe Steps which we complained of, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to ruine him; by the <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>People</hi> both will be ſafe from any repeated Aſſaults of the Prince's Ambition, being ſo well cautioned by the firſt; and ſucceeding Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will be terrified from ſuch Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delities for the future. The Author ſuppoſeth a Caſe which will not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably fall out, and ſo is not weighty enough to reſtrain us from aſſiſting our King in the recovery of his Rights, which poſitive Duty obligeth us unto. And whenever the like Caſe occurs, ſuch corrupt Miniſters, who adviſe ſuch Meaſures, will become a more juſtifiable and eaſier Sacrifice, for the averting ſuch Dangers, than our antient Government and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. And it is pleaſant enough to imagine that wiſe and thinking Men can be impoſed upon to continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der much more weighty Oppreſſions, gr ater and more viſible Dangers, threatning both <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> by K. <hi>William</hi>'s Government, from a fear we may again fall under thoſe leſſer Evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s which we ſuffered under K. <hi>James,</hi> and which were due ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Contrivances of the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>O.</hi> than the King's own depraved In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations. And whereas it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, <hi>That ſuch Pangs of Loyalty are unſeaſonable now, and ſhould rather have been employed for keeping him in his Throne, than reſtoring him to it;</hi> why, truly few People did ſuſpect that the Prince did really deſign what he ſo ſeriouſly and ſolemnly declared againſt; and every Man was ſtruck into a State Lethargy by the ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Prince's Attempt, the wonderful Succ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with in the beginning, and the charmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:47544:30"/>
of ſecuring Liberty and Property; which we are ſadly and ſeverely rowzed from at laſt, by unſpeakable Oppreſſions, by the expiring Groans of Liberty and Property, and by the dreadful View of thoſe Miſeries, which threaten us from all hands and in all Events.</p>
            <p>As to the Obligations we lie under from the Oaths of Allegiance to the preſent Government, the Author himſelf acknowlegeth, That if we be convinced that our Oaths to King <hi>James</hi> are ſtill binding upon us, the Obligation of the ſecond is voided by it, which is a plain enough Anſwer to his own Argument; eſpecially when we conſider, that K. <hi>William</hi>'s manifeſt Infractions of that <hi>Original Contract</hi> which we made with him, upon the maintaining and preſerving of which our Allegiance was expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly founded, doth evidently and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerably diſſolve and make void the Obligation of our Oaths, and much better ſolves all Scruples upon that head, than Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential Reaſoning.</hi> And whereas it is aſſerted by this Author, That Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance can never be expounded to a lower Senſe, than to live peaceably und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the preſent Government, thô we will not ſight for it, and not to attempt any thing again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t their P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Crowns, not to hold Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with their Enemies, nor to give any aſſiſtance to K. <hi>James</hi> for the recovery of his Thrones, in this he hath forgotten their own Practiſe: For our <hi>Reformers</hi> have taught us, That Allegiance may be expounded to a much lower Senſe, even to the <hi>Abdicating</hi> the Monarch to whom the Allegiance was due, to the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his Throne, and transferring of that Allegiance to another; and would take it very ill to be charged with Perjury for it. <hi>Quis tulerit Gracchos de ſeditione loquentes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are exhorted by our Authors to beware of contributing towards K. <hi>James</hi>'s return, leſt we engage our Country in a Civil War, and all the dreadful Conſequences of it; the Deſtruction of our People, the utter Conſumption of our Eſtates, the burning of our Houſes, the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing of our Wives and Daughters, the Extirpation of Families by Sword or Halter, and the utter Ruining our Cities, Towns and Villages, are the infallible Conſequences of it. The mighty deluge of Blood which was ſhed, and the unſpeakable Miſeries which overwhelm'd this Nation, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtruggle betwixt the <hi>Two Roſes,</hi> and our Conteſts with King <hi>Charles</hi> I, are undeniable Proofs, and may convince us how fatal and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive it is to beget and eſtabliſh a Competition of Titles to the Crown, and to dethrone Monarchs: And the Calamities which over-run <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> by the Civil Wars, which begun upon the Account of Religion, may let us ſee how diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it is to God Almighty, to have Religion made a cover for ambitious and private Deſigns. This Civil War is already Commenced, and we have eſtabliſhed thoſe Grounds and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wen that Seed, from which we ſhall not fail to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ap a plentiful Harveſt of Blood and Ruine, without a ſpeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:47544:31"/>
and vigorous Prevention: Nay we have been ſo fond of entailing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Miſery upon our Selves and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities, that we have coupled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two of the ſtrongeſt Motives in the World for a rude and laſting War; <hi>viz.</hi> repeated Breaches in the Royal Line and Succeſſion, and the vacating the Throne upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religion; either of which ſeperately hath never failed to ruine whole Nations, Provinces and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. It is obvious at whoſe Door this is to be Charged; they who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced away their King, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Religion, inverted the Nature of our Monarchy and the Succeſſion, and refuſed all Treaties and Securities which were offered them, have laid infallible Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for thoſe Miſchiefs; and they who wiſh and labour for the return of the King, are the only true and skilful Phyſitians who clearly diſcover, and are willing to apply the moſt proper, nay only Cure, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains for our Diſeaſe: And the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Reaſonings from the Miſeries of a Civil War, doth evidently Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign their own Practiſes; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes moſt forcibly againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as the Promoters of it, ſince it is not to be ſuppoſed, that a juſt Right and Title is to give place to Force and Uſurpation, and fall a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>crifice to thoſe Neceſſities which we firſt bring our ſelves under, and then plead for our Excuſe.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place we are cautioned againſt the King's return, from the intolerable Payments we muſt come under, for refunding thoſe Sums which he hath borrowed of <hi>France,</hi> to maintain Himſelf, to keep <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to diſcharge the Forces that come to thruſt him on us; which will prove a Ten times greater Tax for many Years, than thoſe we pay for the ſupport of this <hi>Government,</hi> which are not conſiderable, reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the abatement of <hi>Chimney-Money;</hi> and are much eaſier than what the French are accuſtomed to; and that we have paid as much formerly for aſſiſting <hi>France</hi> to ruine <hi>Europe,</hi> and maintain Vice at home; and ſo may be very well ſatisfied with our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Payments which delivers <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſecures our native Countrey and Religion from utter Deſtruction. Our celebrated Authors could not have finiſhed their fine Pieces with Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings, which more perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled the Pretences, Motives, and Grounds of this Revolution, by their Weakneſs, Falſhood, and Prevarica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>How well our preſent Payments ſecure our native Countrey and Religion from Deſtruction, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar from the ruine of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Plunderings and free Quarters pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in <hi>Britain,</hi> the Breaches made upon our ancient <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> whereby a War is entailed upon <hi>Us</hi> and our <hi>Poſterity;</hi> from the Violences done to our <hi>Laws, Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Original Contract</hi> made with K. <hi>William;</hi> and from the preſent viſible and eminent Dangers which our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> are threatned with, by any probable Iſſue of this War, under a Prince, who hath quite overturned the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:47544:31"/>
of his own native Countrey, made fair advances towards the ruine of ours; and was never yet Succeſsful in any Enterpriſe he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook, except when he invaded his Father in Law, contrary to all Divine and Humane Rules, (which perhaps God deſigned as a Scourge to theſe Nations for our Sins,) and when he fought <hi>Luxemburgh</hi>'s Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guards, at St. <hi>Denis,</hi> with the Peace in his Pocket, contrary to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith and Law of Nations, as if he were Predeſtinated to be Succeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful only in Crimes, but unfortunate in heroick, brave, and generous Actions; ſuch as reſtraining the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Encroachments of Princes, and vindicating the Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of oppreſſed Nations; having always practiſed in his own Caſe, what he pretended to reform in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other's.</p>
            <p>How little the Deliverance of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> is carried on by our preſent Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is but too evident from the growing Succeſſes of <hi>France</hi> in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and the taking their moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Towns and Fortreſſes in the ſight and under the noſe of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Monarch and thoſe mighty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſederate Armies. It is equally falſe, to inſinuate, That our Payments du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Reign bore any proportion with the Taxes under this; and that they were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed only for aſſiſting <hi>France,</hi> to ruine <hi>Europe:</hi> For the Subſidies we have already paid to this K. (which Sir <hi>Edward S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ymer,</hi> who might very well know it, aſſured the Houſe of Commons, did amount to 18 Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, before the laſt Impoſitions which were granted) do far exceed all the Taxes paid to K. <hi>Charles,</hi> joyn'd with the ſeveral Payments made to our <hi>Edwards,</hi> our <hi>Henries,</hi> and our <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> who raiſed the Honour and Reputation of this Nation ſo high, and ſpread our Conqueſts ſo far: And it was to King <hi>Charles</hi> his Authority and Mediation, the Peaces of <hi>Aix-la-Chapelle</hi> and <hi>Nimiguen</hi> were due, which put then a Stop to the <hi>French</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer: And I am afraid our preſent Payments will very hardly bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Peace again, upon the Foot of thoſe Treaties; and we are to take it as a very great Favour, for which we are to be thankful to God and our preſent King, if the Taxes we pay during this Government, fall any thing ſhort of the <hi>French</hi> Oppreſſions; and Four Millions a Year, over and above an Allowance for the Abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Chimney-Money</hi> and the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Revenues of the Crown, are but inconſiderable Payments in the opinion of theſe Authors. It ſeems their Court Preferments are great and rich, that they are ſo little ſenſible of thoſe Taxes, which are already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo heavy to this Nation, and of which we ſee no end.</p>
            <p>But <hi>the growing Debt to the French King for thoſe Sums already ſpent upon K.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ames<hi>'s Subſiſtance, and the defence of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and to be farther Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nded for his Reſtauration, will quite ſink and undo this Nation.</hi> It appears that theſe Authors take it for granted, That the mercenary Temper of the Dutch, in demanding and obtaining Sati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their Expences, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:47544:32"/>
a tender regard forſooth to our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties they beſtowed upon our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, will be exactly copied by other Princes: But this is the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſuch Merchandiſe; and it is not to be believed, that great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces who ſtudy Fame, and tenderly regard their Honor and Glory, will imitate ſo baſe an Example. But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they ſhould; our Author is as wide in his Eſtimate of this Expence, as in his other Reaſonings. We are frightned with a Charge Ten times bigger, for many Years, than our preſent Payments, and yet will very much fall ſhort of the half of one Years Tax we pay now. The Sums ſpent upon the King's Subſiſtence and <hi>Ireland,</hi> doth not amount to Three hundred thouſand <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dores;</hi> and as for the Charge of his return I wiſh, and heartily pray, that all true Engliſh Men would unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concur together, to prevent the pretence of demanding any ſuch Charges, the neceſſity of Foreign Troops, and even the remoteſt Fears of French Popery and Slavery, by returning our King with as general a Conſent as he was forced from us; which will vindicate the Proteſtant Religion from the reproach of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Principles, and eſtabliſh it for the nature; will reſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e the ancient Monarchy, and Conſtitution of this Nation upon its old Baſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the Injury done to our lawful King, whereby we may legaly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe Securities for our Religion and Liberties, which we are Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unſucceſ fully amidſt ſo many deſpera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs and Diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s; will infallibly relieve us from the weighty Oppreſſions and manifeſt Infractions of our choiceſt and moſt valuable Rights, which we at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent feel, and have ſo much reaſon to be apprehenſive of for the future; will deliver us from the heavy Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of ſo many Taxes, which we have already paid, and which yet muſt be continued if we deſign to ſupport a crazy and unjuſt Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment any longer; which, after all our Blood and Expence muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fall to the ground, and give place to the natural Force and Weight of our ancient Government and Monarchy; to the juſt Title and undoubted Rights of our lawful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign and his Poſterity; to the Love, Affections, and native Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Engliſh Men when the preſent fit is over; and to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of our Neighbouring Princes and States, which lie viſibly croſs unto it, ſo ſoon as their preſent Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences are at an end: And laſtly, by this Method we ſhall be ſecured againſt thoſe fatal Influences upon our Liberties, which never fail to accompany all forced, irreſiſtable, and unexpected returns of Exiled Monarchs.</p>
            <p>I do humbly beſeech Almighty God, That of his Infinite Mercy, for the good of theſe Nations and of all <hi>Europe,</hi> he would open the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Eyes, give him a ſight and diſcovery of the Vanity as well as Injuſtice of poſſeſſing his Father's Throne; and incline his Heart to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh Religion and Liberty among
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:47544:32"/>
us, and give Peace to all <hi>Europe,</hi> by doing an Act which would bury in Oblivion the famed Inſtances of <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> V. and immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize his Name, even by reſtoring his old Father to his Right and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Was it really the Danger our Religion and Liberties were in which put him upon coming to <hi>Britain,</hi> this would be an infallible way fully to ſecure them by new Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, againſt which there lay no Objection: Or was it to put himſelf at the head of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Forces, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to give a Check to the towring Ambition of the <hi>French</hi> Monarch, this would more effectually do it; for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that King would think himſelf obliged, out of Gratitude to a Prince who is truly a Martyr for a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>French</hi> League, to give a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Peace to <hi>Europe,</hi> in order to King <hi>James</hi>'s Reſtauration; or by a Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, our King was at Liberty to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult his own Intereſt, and to unite with the Conſederates by the Advice of Parliament; which would make ſuch a general and vigorous Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces that way, without any fear of Domeſtick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, as would quickly oblige that great Monarch to give ear to Reaſon, and a Peace to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: And the Glory of having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Peace to <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſubdued himſelf, would place the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Name upon the higheſt Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of Fame, furniſh the greateſt Character imaginable for Hiſtory, give a great and noble Example to future Ages, declare him the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor of the Chriſtian World, and oblige all <hi>Britiſh</hi> Subjects to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, that he had moſt generouſly contributed his beſt Endeavours for the ſecuring of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the free Enjoyment of all our Laws, Rights and Liberties, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a juſt and legal Government, according to his <hi>Declaration.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. Col. 1. Line 23. r. <hi>upon a Review of that bl ſſed Occaſion.</hi> p. 8. c. 1. l. 37. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>in.</hi> p. 10. c. 2. l. 9. after Troops, add <hi>to ſupport</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 13. c. 2. l. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it, r. <hi>th y.</hi> p. 14. c. 2. l. 39 r. <hi>eaſie.</hi> p. 21. c. 1. l. 38. r. <hi>was not with.</hi> p. 22. c. 1. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>anoth r.</hi> p. 26. c. 1. l. 13. dele <hi>our.</hi> p. 27. c. 2. l. 21. <hi>r. Princes.</hi> p. 32. c. 1. l. 13. <hi>r. the.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. c. 1. l. 30 dele <hi>upon whole Counties.</hi> p. 37. c. 1. l. 6. after in add <hi>the.</hi> dele <hi>are.</hi> l. 23. r. <hi>Towns.</hi> p. 41. c. 2. l. 3. r. <hi>ſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ening.</hi> p. 43. c. 2 l. 4. dele <hi>and his Deſigns.</hi> p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. c. 2. l. 9. r. <hi>inſtanc.</hi> p. 54 c. 2. l. 32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>fail to furniſh.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
